<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/"><channel><title>My Customized Papers</title><link>https://github.com/your_username/your_repo</link><description>Aggregated research papers</description><language>en-US</language><lastBuildDate>Thu, 15 Jan 2026 01:24:08 GMT</lastBuildDate><generator>rfeed v1.1.1</generator><docs>https://github.com/svpino/rfeed/blob/master/README.md</docs><item><title>[astro-ph update] MUSEQuBES: Investigating the Physical and Chemical Properties of Circumgalactic Gas Around Ly$\alpha$ Emitters at $z \approx 3.3$</title><link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2601.07916</link><description>arXiv:2601.07916v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: We present a detailed study of the physical properties of absorbers associated with $z\approx3.3$ \lya\ emitters (LAEs) from the MUSEQuBES survey. Using \HI\ and ionic column densities derived from Voigt profile fitting, we determine the density and metallicity of 75 absorbers associated with 59 LAEs through a custom-built Bayesian framework. The overall sample shows a median density $\log\,(n_{\rm H}/{\rm cm^{-3}})=-2.7\pm0.7$ and metallicity \met$=-1.6^{+1.2}_{-0.9}$ with $\approx15\%$ ($\approx 40\%$ including upper limits) of systems showing metallicities consistent with the IGM at these redshifts (\met$\lesssim -2.8$). Intriguingly, absorbers with $\log\, N(\rm HI)/{\rm cm^{-2}} \gtrsim 16.5$, corresponding to an overdensity of $\sim 100$ at $z=3$, exhibit a bimodal metallicity distribution with peaks at \met$=-3.8\pm 0.2$ and $-1.8\pm 0.6$. The latter are observed at large impact parameters ($\gtrsim150$~pkpc) and often exhibit low-ionization species (e.g., \SiII, \AlII). We interpret the former as pristine inflowing gas from the cosmic web, while the latter likely traces metal-enriched CGM associated with outflows from faint galaxies not detected in Ly$\alpha$ emission. We find no significant correlations between absorber metallicity or density and host galaxy properties, including redshift, impact parameter, SFR, Ly$\alpha$ luminosity, or environment. Absorbers separated by $\lesssim500$~\kms\ show $\sim$1~dex metallicity and $\sim$0.5~dex density variations, indicating physical and chemical inhomogeneity of the medium around these LAEs.</description><author>astro-ph updates on arXiv.org</author><pubDate>Wed, 14 Jan 2026 05:00:00 GMT</pubDate><guid isPermaLink="true">oai:arXiv.org:2601.07916v1</guid></item><item><title>[astro-ph update] Relativistic jets from millisecond proto-magnetars</title><link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2601.07918</link><description>arXiv:2601.07918v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: Rapidly rotating, strongly magnetized neutron stars (``millisecond proto-magnetars'') formed in stellar core-collapse, neutron star mergers, and white dwarf accretion-induced collapse have long been proposed as central engines of gamma-ray bursts (GRB) and accompanying supernovae/kilonovae. However, during the first few seconds after birth, neutrino heating drives baryon-rich winds from the neutron star surface, potentially limiting the magnetization and achievable Lorentz factors of the outflow and casting doubt on whether proto-magnetars can launch ultra-relativistic jets at early times, as needed to power short-duration GRB. We present 3D general-relativistic magnetohydrodynamic simulations of neutrino-heated proto-magnetar winds that incorporate M0 neutrino transport. While the global wind properties broadly agree with previous analytic estimates calibrated to one-dimensional models, our simulations reveal essential multidimensional effects. For rapidly rotating models with spin periods P = 1 ms, centrifugal forces strongly enhance mass loss near the rotational equator, producing a dense, sub-relativistic outflow ( ~0.1c). This equatorial wind naturally confines and collimates less baryon-loaded outflows emerging from higher latitudes, leading to the formation of a structured bipolar jet with a peak magnetization up to ~ 30-100 along the pole, sufficient to reach bulk Lorentz factors ~ 100 on larger scales. The resulting angular stratification of the outflow energy into ultra-relativistic polar and sub-relativistic equatorial components is broadly consistent with the observed partition between beaming-corrected GRB energies and supernova/kilonova ejecta. Our results demonstrate that millisecond proto-magnetars can launch relativistic jets within seconds of formation and highlight their potential role in powering the diverse electromagnetic counterparts of compact-object explosions.</description><author>astro-ph updates on arXiv.org</author><pubDate>Wed, 14 Jan 2026 05:00:00 GMT</pubDate><guid isPermaLink="true">oai:arXiv.org:2601.07918v1</guid></item><item><title>[astro-ph update] Dense gas linked to star-forming regions photoionised by embedded gamma-ray bursts</title><link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2601.07919</link><description>arXiv:2601.07919v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: The 1-100 pc region embedding long-duration gamma-ray bursts (lGRBs) has been hitherto unexplored, as extremely high ionisation by the GRB prevents application of optical absorption spectroscopy on such distances. We show that the GRB ionising flux imprints a unique time- and spatially-dependent ionisation structure on the gas, that can be probed by X-ray absorption. Application of this model to a selected sample of 7 bright GRB X-ray afterglow spectra observed by \textit{XMM-Newton} EPIC-pn enables an independent, quantitative estimation of the density (log(n) $\sim$ 2-4) and distances (5-100 pc) of the ionized absorber directly from the GRB X-ray spectrum, thereby allowing us to locate the absorbing medium of this representative sample of long GRBs in the region of the density-size diagram populated by star-forming regions versus other gravitationally bound objects in the Universe.</description><author>astro-ph updates on arXiv.org</author><pubDate>Wed, 14 Jan 2026 05:00:00 GMT</pubDate><guid isPermaLink="true">oai:arXiv.org:2601.07919v1</guid></item><item><title>[astro-ph update] A persistent bow shock in a diskless magnetised accreting white dwarf</title><link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2601.07922</link><description>arXiv:2601.07922v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: Stellar bow shocks are formed when an outflow interacts with the interstellar medium. In white dwarfs accreting from a binary companion, outflows are associated with either strong winds from the donor star, the accretion disk, or a thermonuclear runaway explosion on the white dwarf surface. To date, only six accreting white dwarfs are known to harbour disk-wind driven bow shocks that are not associated to thermonuclear explosions. Here, we report the discovery of a bow shock associated with a high-proper-motion disk-less accreting white dwarf, 1RXS J052832.5+283824. We show that the white dwarf has a strong magnetic field in the range B~42-45 MG, making RXJ0528+2838 the a bonafide known polar-type cataclysmic variable harbouring a bow shock. The resolved bow shock is shown to be inconsistent with a past thermonuclear explosion, or being inflated by a donor wind, ruling out all accepted scenarios for inflating a bow shock around this system. Modelling of the energetics reveals that the observed bow shock requires a persistent power source with a luminosity significantly exceeding the system accretion energy output. This implies the presence of a powerful, previously unrecognized energy loss mechanism - potentially tied to magnetic activity - that may operate over sufficiently long timescales to influence the course of binary evolution.</description><author>astro-ph updates on arXiv.org</author><pubDate>Wed, 14 Jan 2026 05:00:00 GMT</pubDate><guid isPermaLink="true">oai:arXiv.org:2601.07922v1</guid></item><item><title>[astro-ph update] The GRB Intrinsic Duration Distribution: Progenitor Insights Across Cosmic Time</title><link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2601.07928</link><description>arXiv:2601.07928v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: We present the distribution of the intrinsic duration of gamma-ray bursts' prompt emission. This expands upon the analysis of Bromberg et al., 2012 and Bromberg et al. 2013 who showed evidence for collapsar progenitors based on the presence of a plateau in the distribution of $T_{90}$, the duration over which 90 % of the prompt emission is observed for any given detector. We confirm the presence of this plateau in the distribution of duration corrected for cosmological time dilation (what we call intrinsic duration, $T_{int}$), but shifted to smaller timescales by a factor of $1/(1+z_{\rm av}) \sim 1/3$, where $z_{\rm av}$ is the average GRB redshift. More significantly, we show this plateau is only present in the sample of GRBs with redshifts greater than $(1+z) \sim 2$, and does not appear in the duration distribution of lower redshift GRBs. This result aligns with suggestions that the low redshift population of GRBs has a significant contribution from non-collapsar progenitors (while the high redshift sample is dominated by collapsars). We also show the difference in this distribution between spectrally hard and soft GRBs, confirming that a plateau is only present for the soft subset of GRBs. However, when we separate the soft GRBs into low and high redshift subsets, we find that only the high redshift soft GRBs show evidence of a plateau, while the low-redshift soft GRBs do not. This suggests there exists a significant subset of spectrally soft non-collapsar progenitors at low redshift. Finally, we use the end time of the plateau to constrain the GRB progenitor density profile and radius, and show the maximum size of a collapsar is a few tenths of a solar radius.</description><author>astro-ph updates on arXiv.org</author><pubDate>Wed, 14 Jan 2026 05:00:00 GMT</pubDate><guid isPermaLink="true">oai:arXiv.org:2601.07928v1</guid></item><item><title>[astro-ph update] Galaxy interactions in void substructures: Morphology and stellar populations of two triplets from CAVITY</title><link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2601.07952</link><description>arXiv:2601.07952v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: Context. Cosmic voids are underdense regions of the Universe that provide a unique environment to study galaxy evolution in relative isolation. Galaxy triplets in voids are rare systems where local interactions may strongly influence galaxy properties.
  Aims. We study the stellar populations, morphologies, mass assembly histories, and dynamical properties of six galaxies belonging to two void triplets from the Calar Alto Void Integral-field Treasury surveY (CAVITY): CAVITY5273X and VGS31.
  Methods. We used integral-field unit spectroscopy and performed full spectral fitting with the FADO code, which models stellar and nebular emission simultaneously. Spatially resolved maps of stellar age, metallicity, and star formation rate were reconstructed using the integrated nested Laplace approximation. Morphological properties were derived using morfometryka, emission-line diagnostics were applied, and mass assembly functions were computed. Stellar masses and metallicities were compared to the mass-metallicity relation for void galaxies.
  Results. The two triplets show different evolutionary behaviours. CAVITY52731 is a massive quenched galaxy hosting an active galactic nucleus, while its companions and all galaxies in VGS31 are dominated by young stellar populations and recent star formation. Five galaxies experienced rapid stellar mass growth in the last 2 Gyr. Disturbed morphologies, including asymmetries and tidal features, indicate ongoing interactions. Galaxies in CAVITY5273X follow the expected void mass-metallicity relation, while VGS31 members show significant deviations.
  Conclusions. Our results show that local interactions can drive significant galaxy evolution even in the most underdense cosmic environments.</description><author>astro-ph updates on arXiv.org</author><pubDate>Wed, 14 Jan 2026 05:00:00 GMT</pubDate><guid isPermaLink="true">oai:arXiv.org:2601.07952v1</guid></item><item><title>[astro-ph update] Evidence of Feedback Effects in Low-luminosity Active Galactic Nuclei Revealed by JWST Spectroscopy</title><link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2601.07990</link><description>arXiv:2601.07990v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: This letter presents an analysis of the infrared ($\sim 3-28\,\mu m$) spectra extracted from the nuclear ($r &lt; 150$ pc) regions of four low-luminosity active galactic nuclei (AGN), observed by JWST NIRSpec/IFU and MIRI/MRS as an extension of the Galaxy Activity, Torus, and Outflow Survey (GATOS). We find that, compared to higher-luminosity AGN, these low-luminosity AGN exhibit distinct properties in their emission of ionized gas, polycyclic aromatic hydrocarbons (PAHs), and molecular hydrogen (H$_2$). Specifically, the low-luminosity AGN exhibit relatively weak high-ionization potential lines (e.g., [Ne V] and [O IV]), and the line ratios suggest that fast radiative shocks (with $v_{\rm s}$ of $\sim \rm 100s\,km\,s^{-1}$) are the primary excitation source of ionized gas therein. Under the low-excitation conditions of their nuclear regions, these low-luminosity AGN generally exhibit a higher fraction of PAHs with large size ($N_{\rm C} \gtrsim 200$), reflecting the preferential destruction of smaller PAH molecules by AGN feedback. Furthermore, the H$_2$ transitions in these low-luminosity AGN are not fully thermalized, with slow, plausibly jet-driven molecular shocks (with $v_{\rm s} \leq \rm 10\,km\,s^{-1}$) likely being the extra excitation source. Taken together with results from the literature, these findings indicate that feedback operates in both low- and high-luminosity AGN, albeit its impact varies with AGN luminosity. In particular, systematic variations in PAH band ratios are found across AGN, demonstrating the differing influence of feedback in AGN of varying luminosities and highlighting the potential of PAH band ratios as diagnostics for distinguishing kinetic- and radiative-mode AGN feedback.</description><author>astro-ph updates on arXiv.org</author><pubDate>Wed, 14 Jan 2026 05:00:00 GMT</pubDate><guid isPermaLink="true">oai:arXiv.org:2601.07990v1</guid></item><item><title>[astro-ph update] Investigating quenching in Recently Quenched Elliptical galaxies with HI studies</title><link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2601.08027</link><description>arXiv:2601.08027v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: Recently Quenched Elliptical galaxies (RQEs) represent a critical phase in the transition from star-forming to quiescent galaxies. However, the mechanisms driving their quenching remain elusive. We conduct a multi-wavelength analysis of 155 RQEs, along with their precursors (preRQEs) and descendants (postRQEs), focusing on their neutral hydrogen (HI) content and star formation properties. Contrary to conventional quenching models emphasizing gas depletion, RQEs retain substantial HI reservoirs ($f_{\text{gas}} \geq 17\%$), suggesting that quenching is not primarily driven by gas exhaustion. We identify a critical halo mass threshold at $\log M_{\text{halo}} = 12.1 M_{\odot}$, delineating different evolutionary pathways for RQEs. This threshold aligns with the transition from cold-mode to hot-mode gas accretion in theoretical models. RQEs in lower-mass halos ($\log M_{\text{halo}} &lt; 12.1 M_{\odot}$) likely experience rapid quenching, possibly initiated by major mergers, followed by brief AGN activity and sustained LINER emission. We propose two evolutionary pathways: (a) rapid quenching via major mergers followed by AGN/LINER activity and passive evolution, and (b) rapid quenching followed by rejuvenation through minor mergers before evolving into more massive, long-term quenched ellipticals. These results challenge the conventional understanding of galaxy quenching, especially in low-density environments where RQEs typically reside. Our findings suggest that while RQEs may follow a rapid quenching pathway, their evolution is influenced by interactions between gas accretion modes, feedback mechanisms, and environmental factors. Future observations with advanced radio interferometers like SKA will be crucial for elucidating the quenching mechanisms in RQEs and their role in galaxy evolution.</description><author>astro-ph updates on arXiv.org</author><pubDate>Wed, 14 Jan 2026 05:00:00 GMT</pubDate><guid isPermaLink="true">oai:arXiv.org:2601.08027v1</guid></item><item><title>[astro-ph update] Long Term (250 years) Hydrodynamical Simulation of the Supermassive Black Hole Binary OJ287</title><link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2601.08080</link><description>arXiv:2601.08080v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: With upcoming facilities capable of detecting photometric and gravitational wave signals from supermassive black hole (SMBH) binaries, studying their long-term accretion-driven variability is timely. OJ287 is a bright, nearby ($z=0.3$), and well-studied candidate for a SMBH binary. As such, it is an excellent case study for how binary dynamics could influence observed active galactic nucleus (AGN) photometric variability. We present 3D hydrodynamic simulations of OJ287, using the code PHANTOM. We simulate two mass ratios: (i) M$_1$ $=$ 1.835$\times$10$^{10}$ M$_\odot$ with M$_2$ $=$ 1.4$\times$10$^{8}$ M$_\odot$, (ii) M$_1\approx$ M$_2$ ($\sim10^{8}$ M$_\odot$) along and (iii) control of a single SMBH and accretion disc. We find that the simulation with masses 1.835$\times$10$^{10}$ M$_\odot$ and 1.4$\times$10$^{8}$ M$_\odot$ evolves consistently with the most currently accepted model of OJ287 as a precessing SMBH binary. The secondary's impacts with the disc result in the formation of spiral density waves and a corresponding $\sim$10-20% increases in the mass accretion rate of the primary SMBH. The impact timings and the mass accretion rate spikes show quasi-periodic variability as a result of the precession of the secondary's orbit with intervals between impacts ranging from $\sim$ 1 year to $\sim$ 10 years. In the near-equal mass case, the disc of the primary becomes tidally disrupted after $\sim$ 2 years. Consequently, the near-equal mass system with a period of 12 years is not a viable candidate for OJ287. This modeling provides insights into the potential signatures of SMBH binaries by both gravitational wave observatories and the Rubin Legacy Survey of Space and Time.</description><author>astro-ph updates on arXiv.org</author><pubDate>Wed, 14 Jan 2026 05:00:00 GMT</pubDate><guid isPermaLink="true">oai:arXiv.org:2601.08080v1</guid></item><item><title>[astro-ph update] Evaluating the effectiveness of radio frequency interference removal algorithms for single pulse searches</title><link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2601.08351</link><description>arXiv:2601.08351v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: Radio Frequency Interference (RFI), the presence of artificial and/or terrestrial signals in astronomical data, poses a great challenge to the search for pulsars and radio transients, such as Rotating Radio Transients (RRATs) and Fast Radio Bursts (FRBs), by obscuring or distorting the signal of interest and resulting in large numbers of erroneous detections. RFI mitigation algorithms aim to remove this interference and improve the chance of detection of transients, but with the growing number of techniques, selecting the most appropriate method for a given survey can be problematic. The choice of method is particularly important in real-time searches planned for next-generation telescopes such as those of the SKAO, where there is no possibility to reprocess the data. In this paper, we explore the algorithm selection problem by injecting pulses into data which simulates several RFI environments. A set of these files is then cleaned using RFI mitigation algorithms and run through a single pulse search pipeline to analyse the recovery of the injected pulses. We examine the recovery of the injected single pulses with an emphasis on a number of cases spanning a range of pulse brightness, width and dispersion measure. The efficacy and side effects of a few popular RFI excision methods, namely IQRM, SKF, and ZDMF are evaluated.</description><author>astro-ph updates on arXiv.org</author><pubDate>Wed, 14 Jan 2026 05:00:00 GMT</pubDate><guid isPermaLink="true">oai:arXiv.org:2601.08351v1</guid></item><item><title>[astro-ph update] Stellar masses of optically dark galaxies: uncertainty introduced by the attenuation law and star-formation histories</title><link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2601.08693</link><description>arXiv:2601.08693v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: JWST observations have suggested that some high-redshift galaxies may be ultra-massive, thereby challenging standard models of early galaxy formation and cosmology. We analyse the stellar masses using different modelling assumptions and with new data of three galaxies (S1, S2 and S3), whose NIRCam/grism redshifts were consistent with $z&gt;5$. These three optically dark galaxies have previously been reported to host exceptionally high stellar masses and star-formation rates, implying extremely high star-formation efficiencies. Recent NIRSpec/IFU observations for S1 indicate a spectroscopic redshift of $z_{\rm spec}=3.2461^{+0.0001}_{-0.0002}$, which is lower than previously reported. Using the Bayesian spectral energy distribution (SED) modelling tool \texttt{Prospector}, we investigate the impact of key model assumptions on stellar mass estimates, such as the choice of star-formation history (SFH) priors (constant versus rising SFH base for the non-parametric prior), the dust attenuation law, and the treatment of emission line fluxes. Our analysis yields revised stellar masses of $\log(M_{\star}/M_{\odot}) \approx 10.36^{+0.47}_{-0.32}, 10.95^{+0.11}_{-0.10}$ and $10.31^{+0.24}_{-0.19}$ for S1, S2, and S3, respectively. We find that adopting a rising SFH base prior results in lower inferred stellar masses compared to a constant SFH base prior. We identify a significant degeneracy between the dust attenuation curve slope, the amount of dust attenuation, and stellar mass. Our results highlight various systematics in SED modelling due to SFH priors and dust attenuation that can influence stellar mass estimates of heavily dust obscured sources. Nevertheless, even with these revised stellar mass estimates, two of the three galaxies remain among the most massive and actively star-forming systems at their respective redshifts, implying high star-formation efficiencies.</description><author>astro-ph updates on arXiv.org</author><pubDate>Wed, 14 Jan 2026 05:00:00 GMT</pubDate><guid isPermaLink="true">oai:arXiv.org:2601.08693v1</guid></item><item><title>[astro-ph update] Evolution and afterglow emission of gamma-ray burst jets from binary neutron star mergers</title><link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2601.08714</link><description>arXiv:2601.08714v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: Relativistic jets launched in binary neutron star (BNS) mergers are widely accepted as the engines powering most of the population of short gamma-ray bursts (GRBs). Understanding their structure and dynamics-particularly during and after breakout from the merger ejecta-is crucial for interpreting GRB afterglows, especially for off-axis observers. Traditional models often assume simple angular or radial jet profiles, potentially missing key features emerging for jets piercing through realistic environments. This work aims to investigate the formation and evolution of the jet structure as it propagates through a non-homogeneous, anisotropic BNS merger environment. We focus on how the interaction with the ambient medium shapes the jet's angular and velocity distributions and assess the impact of this realistic structure on the resulting afterglow light curves. We perform a series of 3D relativistic magnetohydrodynamic simulations of jets launched in post-merger environments, exploring different injection conditions. Simulations are evolved to late times, approaching the ballistic regime, where further dynamical evolution becomes negligible. From the resulting outflows, we extract energy and velocity profiles and compute multi-wavelength afterglow light curves using a semi-analytic model that includes radial stratification and the full 3D jet geometry. More energetic or earlier-launched jets drill more efficiently through the ejecta, but all develop asymmetries that leave clear imprints in the off-axis afterglow light curves. All models exhibit a complex multi-shock breakout structure responsible for an early, dimmer peak in the afterglow. Despite structural differences, all simulated jets are consistent with the observational data of the multi-messenger BNS merger event GW170817.</description><author>astro-ph updates on arXiv.org</author><pubDate>Wed, 14 Jan 2026 05:00:00 GMT</pubDate><guid isPermaLink="true">oai:arXiv.org:2601.08714v1</guid></item><item><title>[astro-ph update] A precessing jet from an active galactic nucleus drives gas outflow from a disk galaxy</title><link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2601.08791</link><description>arXiv:2601.08791v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: To reproduce observed galaxy properties, cosmological simulations require that massive galaxies experience feedback from active galactic nuclei, which regulates star formation within those galaxies. However, the energetics and timescales of these feedback processes are poorly constrained. We combine optical, infrared, sub-millimeter and radio observations of the active galaxy VV 340a, hosting a low-power jet launched from a supermassive black hole at its center. We find that the jet undergoes precession, with a period of (8.2 $\pm~$5.5) $\times~$10$^5$ years, and drives an outflow of gas at a rate of 19.4 $\pm~$7.9 solar masses per year. The jet shocks the gas, producing highly ionized plasma extending several kiloparsecs from the nucleus. The outflow ejects sufficient gas from the galaxy to influence its star formation rate.</description><author>astro-ph updates on arXiv.org</author><pubDate>Wed, 14 Jan 2026 05:00:00 GMT</pubDate><guid isPermaLink="true">oai:arXiv.org:2601.08791v1</guid></item><item><title>[astro-ph update] Ghost-free non-local $F(R)$ Gravity Compatible with ACT</title><link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2601.07879</link><description>arXiv:2601.07879v1 Announce Type: cross 
Abstract: We confront the ghost-free non-local $F(R)$ gravity theories with the latest Atacama Cosmology Telescope (ACT) constraints on the spectral index of the scalar perturbations and the updated constraints of Planck/BICEP on the tensor-to-scalar ratio. After reviewing how the ghost-free non-local version of $F(R)$ gravity can be obtained, we show that the de Sitter solution can be obtained in this framework. Also, we show that the resulting theory can be cast in terms of an $F(R,\phi)$ theory of gravity. We analyze two models of non-local $F(R)$ gravity, one power-law and the $R^2$ model, and we show that both models can be compatible with the ACT and updated Planck/BICEP constraints.</description><author>astro-ph updates on arXiv.org</author><pubDate>Wed, 14 Jan 2026 05:00:00 GMT</pubDate><guid isPermaLink="true">oai:arXiv.org:2601.07879v1</guid></item><item><title>[astro-ph update] Revisiting The Cosmological Time Dilation of Distant Quasars: Influence of Source Properties and Evolution</title><link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2501.04171</link><description>arXiv:2501.04171v2 Announce Type: replace 
Abstract: After decades of searching, cosmological time dilation was recently identified in the timescale of variability seen in distant quasars. Here, we expand on the previous analysis to disentangle this cosmological signal from the influence of the properties of the source population, specifically the quasar bolometric luminosity and the rest-frame emission wavelength at which the variability was observed. Furthermore, we consider the potential influence of the evolution of the quasar population over cosmic time. We find that a significant intrinsic scatter of 0.288 +- 0.021 dex in the variability timescales, which was not considered in the previous analysis, is favoured by the data. This slightly increases the uncertainty in the results. However, the expected cosmological dependence of the variability timescales is confirmed to be robust to changes in the underlying assumptions. We find that the variability timescales increase smoothly with both wavelength and bolometric luminosity, and that black hole mass has no effect on the variability timescale once rest wavelength and bolometric luminosity are accounted for. Moreover, if the standard cosmological model is correct, governed by relativistic expansion, we also find very little cosmological evolution in the intrinsic variability timescales of distant quasars.</description><author>astro-ph updates on arXiv.org</author><pubDate>Wed, 14 Jan 2026 05:00:00 GMT</pubDate><guid isPermaLink="true">oai:arXiv.org:2501.04171v2</guid></item><item><title>[astro-ph update] Power Suppression and Lensing Anomaly -- A phenomenological investigation</title><link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2504.21386</link><description>arXiv:2504.21386v3 Announce Type: replace 
Abstract: Primordial power spectra with low power at long wavelengths can alleviate lensing anomaly. However the extent to which data favours such a primordial spectra is not clear. In this work, we investigate power suppression and related mitigation of lensing anomaly with the help of phenomenological models which are valid over scales of interest. We consider simple extensions to nearly scale invariant power spectra such as those which includes running and running of running of spectral index. We perform Bayesian analysis of these models, which are agnostic about power suppression, with Planck legacy data and show that data tend to choose parameters which leads to power suppression at low multipoles. We then investigate the connection between power suppression and alleviation of lensing anomaly and show that lensing anomaly is mitigated the most in models with maximum suppression of power at low multipoles. We also analyse the significance of these findings using information criteria. These results are further analyzed in the light of Planck Release 4 data using CamSpec, HiLLiPoP and LoLLiPoP likelihoods in which departure of lensing parameter from one is significantly reduced. Furthermore, we investigate the ability of near-ultimate future CMB missions such as ECHO to put tighter constraints on these models and to settle the issue. We conclude that we can make stronger conclusions about the presence of power suppression in the future by studying such simple phenomenological models.</description><author>astro-ph updates on arXiv.org</author><pubDate>Wed, 14 Jan 2026 05:00:00 GMT</pubDate><guid isPermaLink="true">oai:arXiv.org:2504.21386v3</guid></item><item><title>[astro-ph update] The Dichotomy in the Nuclear and Host Galaxy Properties of High-redshift Quasars</title><link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2505.12867</link><description>arXiv:2505.12867v2 Announce Type: replace 
Abstract: The early growth of high-redshift quasars and their host galaxies raises critical questions about their cosmic evolution. We exploit the angular resolution and sensitivity of NIRCam to investigate the host galaxies of 31 quasars at $4\lesssim z\lesssim7$ drawn from multiple JWST surveys. Using a new multi-band forward-modeling code (\textsc{GalfitS}) that incorporates physically motivated priors, we securely detect and quantify the host emission in 30 objects, while simultaneously characterizing the nuclear spectral energy distribution. The host galaxies of high-redshift quasars are $\sim 0.3$~dex more compact than star-forming galaxies of comparable mass. A striking dichotomy emerges: luminous ``blue'' quasars ($L_{5100}\gtrsim10^{45}\,{\rm erg\,s^{-1}}$) reside in bulge-dominated galaxies ($n \approx 5$) and exhibit a narrow range of ultraviolet nuclear slopes (median $\beta_{\rm UV} \approx -1.4$), while fainter ``red'' quasars inhabit disk-like hosts ($n\approx 1$) and display a broad range of slopes ($\beta_{\rm UV}\approx-2$ to 4). These two populations differ markedly in their black hole-to-stellar mass ratios, with high-luminosity quasars showing $M_{\mathrm{BH}}/M_\ast = 1.2\%$ compared to $4.7\%$ for lower luminosity sources, placing them collectively $\sim$0.6~dex above the local $M_{\mathrm{BH}}-M_\ast$ relation. This offset likely reflects rapid black hole growth in early gas-rich environments, where feedback from the active galactic nucleus becomes effective only after substantial gas depletion. Our findings suggest that the observed dichotomy, whether due to intrinsic spectral differences or dust extinction, fundamentally shapes the coevolution of supermassive black holes and their host galaxies in the early Universe.</description><author>astro-ph updates on arXiv.org</author><pubDate>Wed, 14 Jan 2026 05:00:00 GMT</pubDate><guid isPermaLink="true">oai:arXiv.org:2505.12867v2</guid></item><item><title>[astro-ph update] Chasing Serendipity: Tackling Transient Sources with Neutrino Telescopes</title><link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2505.24652</link><description>arXiv:2505.24652v2 Announce Type: replace 
Abstract: The discovery of ultra-high-energy neutrinos by IceCube marked the beginning of neutrino astronomy. Yet, the origin and production mechanisms of these neutrinos remain an open question. With the observation of several neutrino events with energies about the PeV, transient sources - astrophysical objects that emit particles in brief, localized bursts - have emerged as promising candidates. In this work, we revisit the identification of such sources in IceCube and future neutrino telescopes, focusing on how both the timing and sky localization of the source affect the detection sensitivity. We present a framework to account for the source's right ascension in determining the effective area of detectors not located at the poles, such as KM3NeT. As a case study, we investigate evaporating primordial black holes (PBHs) as transient neutrino sources, showing that the detection prospects and localization accuracy are strongly influenced by the PBH's position in the sky. Our results emphasize the complementarity between neutrino and gamma-ray observatories and showcase the potential of a global network of neutrino detectors to identify and localize transient events that might be missed by traditional photon-based instruments.</description><author>astro-ph updates on arXiv.org</author><pubDate>Wed, 14 Jan 2026 05:00:00 GMT</pubDate><guid isPermaLink="true">oai:arXiv.org:2505.24652v2</guid></item><item><title>[astro-ph update] The impact of kilonova seed photons on GRB VHE emission</title><link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2507.21233</link><description>arXiv:2507.21233v2 Announce Type: replace 
Abstract: Over the last several years, there have been a number of GRBs with very high energy (VHE) emission in excess of 100 GeV, and even above 1 TeV, detected. In several instances, synchrotron seed photons do not fully explain the emission observed, suggesting the presence of other seed photon sources to up-scatter. In this work, we consider the kilonova as a source of seed photons for up-scattering in the afterglow. We model the kilonova as a thermal source injecting into the back of a GRB fireball, evolved using a shell model, and with the electron and photon populations updated via a kinetic solver. We find that VHE emission from weaker afterglows, such as those found in short GRBs, can be affected by such seed photons, with the kilonova seed photons mitigating the loss of synchrotron photons on the VHE emission when afterglow parameters are varied. We also find that VHE emission in structured jets, due to weaker synchrotron emission at their wings, can also benefit from this supply of seed photons, especially when viewed off-axis. We apply this model to GRB 170817A, and show that its VHE spectral flux is higher than expected in previous models for the first 100 d, though still below the detection threshold.</description><author>astro-ph updates on arXiv.org</author><pubDate>Wed, 14 Jan 2026 05:00:00 GMT</pubDate><guid isPermaLink="true">oai:arXiv.org:2507.21233v2</guid></item><item><title>[astro-ph update] A $\tau-$DM relation for FRB hosts?</title><link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2508.13317</link><description>arXiv:2508.13317v3 Announce Type: replace 
Abstract: It has been proposed that measurements of scattering times ($\tau$) from fast radio bursts (FRB) may be used to infer the FRB host dispersion measure (DM) and its redshift. This approach relies on the existence of a correlation between $\tau$ and DM within FRB hosts such as that observed for Galactic pulsars. We assess the measurability of a $\tau - $DM$_{\rm host}$ relation through simulated observations of FRBs within the ASKAP/CRAFT survey, taking into account instrumental effects. We show that even when the FRB hosts intrinsically follow the $\tau - $DM relation measured for pulsars, this correlation cannot be inferred from FRB observations; this limitation arises mostly from the large variance around the average cosmic DM value given by the Macquart relation, the variance within the $\tau - $DM relation itself, and observational biases against large $\tau$ values. We argue that theoretical relations have little utility as priors on redshift, e.g., for purposes of galaxy identification, and that the recent lack of an observed correlation between scattering and DM in the ASKAP/CRAFT survey is not unexpected, even if our understanding of a $\tau - $DM$_{\rm host}$ relation is correct.</description><author>astro-ph updates on arXiv.org</author><pubDate>Wed, 14 Jan 2026 05:00:00 GMT</pubDate><guid isPermaLink="true">oai:arXiv.org:2508.13317v3</guid></item><item><title>[astro-ph update] SN 2024hpj: A perspective on SN 2009ip-like events</title><link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2508.14579</link><description>arXiv:2508.14579v2 Announce Type: replace 
Abstract: Supernovae (SNe) IIn are terminal explosions of massive stars that are surrounded by a dense circumstellar medium (CSM). Among SNe IIn, a notable subset is the SN 2009ip-like, which exhibits an initial, fainter peak attributed to stellar variability in the late evolutionary stages, followed by a brighter peak, interpreted as the SN explosion itself. In this context, we analysed the spectrophotometric evolution of SN 2024hpj, an object with a triple-peaked light curve and spectra typical of a SN IIn but with a complex line profile composed of broad P-Cygni features topped by narrow emissions. Comparing it with other SN 2009ip-like events in the literature, as well as with other unpublished objects (SNe 2019mry, 2022ytx, 2024uzf, and 2025csc), we identify star-forming regions as their preferred formation environment. On the other hand, the diversity of spectrophotometric features within the sample suggests that variations in CSM mass and distribution may influence the observed characteristics. We identify four sub-classes based on the luminosity and rapidity of the light curve evolution, which provides insights into possible differences in the progenitors, while a statistical analysis of their observed rate indicates progenitor masses around 25 - 31 solar masses or lower.</description><author>astro-ph updates on arXiv.org</author><pubDate>Wed, 14 Jan 2026 05:00:00 GMT</pubDate><guid isPermaLink="true">oai:arXiv.org:2508.14579v2</guid></item><item><title>[astro-ph update] 1.8 per cent measurement of $H_0$ from Cepheids alone</title><link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2509.09665</link><description>arXiv:2509.09665v2 Announce Type: replace 
Abstract: One of the most pressing problems in current cosmology is the cause of the Hubble tension. We revisit a two-rung distance ladder, composed only of Cepheid periods and magnitudes, anchor distances in the Milky Way, Large Magellanic Cloud, NGC 4258, and host galaxy redshifts. We adopt the SH0ES data for the most up-to-date and carefully vetted measurements, where the Cepheid hosts were selected to harbour also Type Ia supernovae. We introduce two important improvements: a rigorous selection modelling and a state-of-the-art density and peculiar velocity model using Manticore-Local, based on the Bayesian Origin Reconstruction from Galaxies (BORG) algorithm. We infer $H_0 = 71.7 \pm 1.3\,\mathrm{km}\,\mathrm{s}^{-1}\,\mathrm{Mpc}^{-1}$, assuming the Cepheid host sample was selected by supernova magnitudes. However, the actual selection criteria are not clear, and other assumptions can increase $H_0$ by up to one statistical standard deviation. The posterior has a lower central value and a 45 per cent smaller uncertainty than a previous study using the same distance-ladder data. The result is also slightly lower than the supernova-based SH0ES inferred value of $H_0 = 73.2 \pm 0.9\,\mathrm{km}\,\mathrm{s}^{-1}\,\mathrm{Mpc}^{-1}$, and is in $3.3\sigma$ tension with the latest cosmic microwave background results in the standard cosmological model. These results demonstrate that a measurement of $H_0$ of sufficient precision to weigh in on the Hubble tension is achievable using second-rung data alone, underscoring the importance of robust and accurate statistical and velocity-field modelling.</description><author>astro-ph updates on arXiv.org</author><pubDate>Wed, 14 Jan 2026 05:00:00 GMT</pubDate><guid isPermaLink="true">oai:arXiv.org:2509.09665v2</guid></item><item><title>[astro-ph update] Impact of Neutrino Flavor Conversions on Neutron Star Merger Dynamics, Ejecta, Nucleosynthesis, and Multi-Messenger Signals</title><link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2510.15028</link><description>arXiv:2510.15028v2 Announce Type: replace 
Abstract: We present numerical relativity simulations of binary neutron star mergers incorporating neutrino flavor transformations triggered by fast flavor instability, quantum many-body effects, or potential beyond standard model physics. In both long-lived and short-lived remnant scenarios, neutrino flavor conversions modify species-dependent neutrino luminosities and mean energies, and drive the matter towards more neutron rich conditions. They produce up to $300\%$ more neutron rich ejecta and significantly boost the r-process yields, especially in low-density, near-equatorial outflows. We identify regions unstable to fast flavor instabilities and find that these instabilities persist despite flavor conversions. We further test the sensitivity to the equilibration timescale of the flavor conversions, finding that slower flavor conversions can interact with thermodynamic equilibration, and increase the neutron richness of the ejecta. Flavor conversions may also contribute to stronger gravitational wave and neutrino emissions, pointing to a correlation between neutrino transport and merger dynamics. These results highlight the potential impact of flavor conversions while motivating future work to improve on theoretical understanding of flavor instabilities in global simulations.</description><author>astro-ph updates on arXiv.org</author><pubDate>Wed, 14 Jan 2026 05:00:00 GMT</pubDate><guid isPermaLink="true">oai:arXiv.org:2510.15028v2</guid></item><item><title>[astro-ph update] PHANGS-JWST: the largest extragalactic molecular cloud catalog traced by polycyclic aromatic hydrocarbon emission</title><link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2511.06596</link><description>arXiv:2511.06596v2 Announce Type: replace 
Abstract: High-resolution JWST images of nearby spiral galaxies reveal polycyclic aromatic hydrocarbon (PAH) emission structures that trace molecular gas, including CO-dark regions. We identify ISM cloud structures in PHANGS-JWST 7.7 $\mu$m PAH maps for 66 galaxies, smoothed to 30 pc and at native resolution, extracting 108,466 and 146,040 clouds, respectively. Molecular properties were inferred using a linear conversion from PAH to CO. Given the tendency for clouds in galaxy centers to overlap in velocity space, we opted to flag these and omit them from the analysis in this work. The remaining clouds correspond to giant molecular clouds, such as those detected in CO(2-1) emission by ALMA, or lower surface density clouds that either fall below the ALMA detection limits of existing maps or genuinely have no molecular counterpart. Cross-matching with ALMA CO maps at 90 pc in 27 galaxies shows that 41 % of PAH clouds have CO associations. The converted molecular properties vary little across environments, but the most massive clouds are preferentially found in spiral arms. Fitting lognormal mass distributions down to $2\times10^{3} M_{\odot}$ shows that spiral arms host the highest-mass clouds, consistent with enhanced formation in arm gravitational potentials. Cloud molecular surface densities decline by a factor of $\sim 1.5-2$ toward $2 - 3 R_{e}$. However, the trend largely varies in individual galaxies, with flat, decreasing, and even no trend as a function of galactocentric radius. Factors like large-scale processes and morphologies might influence the observed trends. We publish two catalogs online, one at the common resolution of 30 pc and another at the native resolution. We expect them to have broad utility for future PAH clouds, molecular clouds, and star formation studies.</description><author>astro-ph updates on arXiv.org</author><pubDate>Wed, 14 Jan 2026 05:00:00 GMT</pubDate><guid isPermaLink="true">oai:arXiv.org:2511.06596v2</guid></item><item><title>[astro-ph update] J-HERTz: J-PLUS Heritage Exploration of Radio Targets at z $&lt;$ 5</title><link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2511.14844</link><description>arXiv:2511.14844v2 Announce Type: replace 
Abstract: We introduce J-HERTz (J-PLUS Heritage Exploration of Radio Targets at $z &lt; 5$), a new multi-wavelength catalog that combines optical narrow-band photometry from J-PLUS, infrared observations from WISE, and deep low-frequency radio data from LoTSS for nearly half a million sources across 2,100 deg$^2$ of the northern sky. Key innovations of J-HERTz include Bayesian neural network classifications for 390,000 galaxies, 31,000 quasars, and 20,000 stars, along with significantly improved photometric redshifts for 235,000 galaxies compared to previous J-PLUS DR3 and LoTSS DR2 estimates. We identify 831 candidate Galactic radio stars, which, if confirmed, would constitute a significant addition to the number of radio-emitting stars identified to date. Among radio-loud galaxies with spectroscopic observations, $\gtrsim$20% lack Seyfert or LINER signatures, indicating a substantial population of optically quiescent radio galaxies, in agreement with previous works. Spectral energy distribution fitting of their host galaxies using J-PLUS photospectra reveals systematically low specific star formation rates, consistent with quenched stellar populations. J-HERTz thus provides a powerful dataset to exploit radio-optical synergies, enabling studies that span from the origin of stellar radio emission to the AGN life cycle and the role of jet activity in shaping host galaxy evolution.</description><author>astro-ph updates on arXiv.org</author><pubDate>Wed, 14 Jan 2026 05:00:00 GMT</pubDate><guid isPermaLink="true">oai:arXiv.org:2511.14844v2</guid></item><item><title>[astro-ph update] A secondary orbiter under collisions with an accretion disk</title><link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2512.23826</link><description>arXiv:2512.23826v2 Announce Type: replace 
Abstract: Dynamics of stellar orbits in dense stellar systems and nuclear star clusters (NSC) with an embedded supermassive black hole (SMBH) is governed a complex interplay of different forces. In particular, star--star gravitational collisions (relaxation), physical collisions between stars, and the hydrodynamical interaction with any surrounding gaseous environment, such as an accretion disk. These processes influence the stellar distribution, the feeding of the central black hole, and the generation of observable phenomena. Furthermore, the self-gravity of the accretion medium modulates the long-term evolution, adding significant complexity to the system's dynamics. By employing elementary arguments we outline the mentioned influences in their mutual competition.</description><author>astro-ph updates on arXiv.org</author><pubDate>Wed, 14 Jan 2026 05:00:00 GMT</pubDate><guid isPermaLink="true">oai:arXiv.org:2512.23826v2</guid></item><item><title>[astro-ph update] Magnetic field dynamics in presence of Hall conductivity and thermo-diffusion</title><link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2506.02202</link><description>arXiv:2506.02202v2 Announce Type: replace-cross 
Abstract: Anisotropy of kinetic coefficients in presence of a magnetic field is
  represented by Hall currents, which appear in a collisional medium due to action of the Lorentz force on the charged particles between collisions.
  We derive equations, describing dynamics of the magnetic field in presence of thermo-diffusion with Hall currents, using a standard electrodynamic consideration. The influence of the Hall currents, at presence of thermo-diffusion, on the magnetic field structure is considered in simple models. The equation is derived, which includes additional term for a seed magnetic field creation in the non-magnetized plasma, due to thermo-diffusion. This equation describes the action of the seed magnetic field creation by the mechanism known as "Biermann battery".</description><author>astro-ph updates on arXiv.org</author><pubDate>Wed, 14 Jan 2026 05:00:00 GMT</pubDate><guid isPermaLink="true">oai:arXiv.org:2506.02202v2</guid></item><item><title>[The Astrophysic] The Large-scale Environments of Low-luminosity AGNs at 3.9 &lt; z &lt; 6 and Implications for Their Host Dark Matter Halos from a Complete NIRCam Grism Redshift Survey</title><link>https://iopscience.iop.org/article/10.3847/1538-4357/ae1eef</link><description>We study the large-scale environments and clustering properties of 28 low-luminosity active galactic nuclei (AGNs) at z = 3.9â€“6 in the GOODS-N field. Our sample, identified from the JWST NIRCam Imaging and WFSS data in Complete NIRCam Grism Redshift Survey and First Reionization Epoch Spectroscopically Complete Observations surveys with either broad HÎ± emission lines or V-shaped continua, are compared to 782 HÎ± emitters (HAEs) selected from the same data. These AGNs are located in diverse large-scale environments and do not preferentially reside in denser environments compared to HAEs. Their overdensity field, Î´, averaged over (15 hâˆ’1 cMpc)3, ranges from âˆ’0.56 to 10.56, and shows no clear correlation with broad-line luminosity, black hole (BH) masses, or the AGN fraction. It suggests that &gt;10 cMpc structures do not significantly influence BH growth. We measure the two-point cross-correlation function of AGNs with HAEs, finding a comparable amplitude to that of the HAE autocorrelation. This indicates similar bias parameters and host dark matter halo masses for AGNs and HAEs. The correlation length of field AGNs is 4.26 hâˆ’1 cMpc and 7.66 hâˆ’1 cMpc at 3.9 &lt; z &lt; 5 and 5 &lt; z &lt; 6, respectively. We infer a median host dark matter halo mass of and host stellar masses of by comparing with the UniverseMachine simulation. Our clustering analysis suggests that low-luminosity AGNs at high redshift reside in normal star-forming galaxies with overmassive BHs. They represent an intrinsically distinct population from luminous quasars and could be a common phase in galaxy evolution.</description><author>The Astrophysical Journal - latest papers</author><pubDate>Wed, 14 Jan 2026 00:00:00 GMT</pubDate><guid isPermaLink="true">https://iopscience.iop.org/article/10.3847/1538-4357/ae1eef</guid></item><item><title>[The Astrophysic] Gas Accretion from a Neighbouring Galaxy Fuels the Low-luminosity Active Galactic Nucleus in NGC 4278</title><link>https://iopscience.iop.org/article/10.3847/1538-4357/ae2fbd</link><description>How a seemingly â€œdeadâ€ host galaxy provides fuel for its active galactic nucleus (AGN) remains an unresolved problem. Using the Five-hundred-meter Aperture Spherical radio Telescope (FAST), we present a new high-sensitivity atomic-hydrogen (H i) observation toward the nearby elliptical galaxy NGC 4278 and its adjacent region. From the observation, we found that external gas accretion from a neighbouring galaxy fuels the low-luminosity AGN in NGC 4278 through tidal interactions. The accreted gas entering NGC 4278 exhibits a rotating gas disk. Moreover, the accreted galaxy has been gas poor and has an H i to stellar mass ratio of about 0.02. Due to the process of gas accretion, it is likely that relativistic jets are generated in the AGN of NGC 4278. The emission of TeV gamma rays in NGC 4278 is likely to be associated with the newly accreted H i gas.</description><author>The Astrophysical Journal - latest papers</author><pubDate>Wed, 14 Jan 2026 00:00:00 GMT</pubDate><guid isPermaLink="true">https://iopscience.iop.org/article/10.3847/1538-4357/ae2fbd</guid></item><item><title>[The Astrophysic] Magnetic Activity in M-type Stars Based on LAMOST DR11 and TESS Observations</title><link>https://iopscience.iop.org/article/10.3847/1538-4365/ae2461</link><description>We have used 898,351 M-type stellar spectra released by Large Sky Area Multi-Object Fiber Spectroscopic Telescope DR11 to calculate the equivalent width of the Ca II infrared triplet (IRT) lines, the residual chromospheric emission, and the parameter , which is defined as the ratio of the luminosity of the 8542 Ã… line to the stellar bolometric luminosity. The chromospheric activity of M dwarfs reaches its maximum around an effective temperature of 3700 K, corresponding to a spectral type of approximately M6. The stellar photospheric activity begins to become significant at around 3800 K, and the trend gradually becomes weaker when approaching 3200 K, which may be due to the influence of the magnetic activity saturation zone. Furthermore, metallicity also influences the intensity of the chromospheric activity. We found that chromospheric and photospheric activity in M dwarfs are correlated, and that both types of activity are influenced by stellar rotation. Additionally, we crossmatched our catalog with the Transiting Exoplanet Survey Satellite and identified 23,079 flare events from 3280 stars. Our results show that the majority of the M dwarf flare radiation energy is below 1036 erg, and the flare duration and energy of nearly all spectral types follow a power-law distribution, i.e., with Î± = 2. For the cumulative flare frequency distributionâ€™s power-law index, we found the range to be between 1.44 and 2. We found that the power-law index Î± for fully convective M-type stars is approximately 1.61 Â± 0.08, while for nonâ€“fully convective M-type stars, it is around 1.78 Â± 0.11.</description><author>The Astrophysical Journal Supplement Series - latest papers</author><pubDate>Wed, 14 Jan 2026 00:00:00 GMT</pubDate><guid isPermaLink="true">https://iopscience.iop.org/article/10.3847/1538-4365/ae2461</guid></item><item><title>[The Astrophysic] Quantifying How Surface Complexity Influences Properties of the Solar Corona and Solar Wind</title><link>https://iopscience.iop.org/article/10.3847/1538-4357/ae197a</link><description>The Sunâ€™s magnetic field is a key driver in coronal heating and consequently solar wind acceleration. Remote measurement of the photosphere provides the magnetic surface boundary condition necessary for data-constrained 3D global coronal models. With one such model, we explore how the spatial resolution of the surface boundary condition influences the global properties of the magnetic field and coronal heating. Using spherical harmonic decomposition, we quantify how three different resolution simulations vary in the low and middle corona. Through examination of the magnetic field, the squashing factor, and the heating rate, we demonstrate that small-scale photospheric magnetic flux enhances heating across spatial regimes. We calculate 40% more heating in our best-resolution simulation compared to our base resolution. We describe a strong correlation between the structure of the magnetic field and the structure of the heating rate in the low corona across resolutions. These results provide key information as to what more efficient, low-resolution models might inherently miss. This can provide context to incorporate the effects of unresolvable features in future modeling efforts.</description><author>The Astrophysical Journal - latest papers</author><pubDate>Wed, 14 Jan 2026 00:00:00 GMT</pubDate><guid isPermaLink="true">https://iopscience.iop.org/article/10.3847/1538-4357/ae197a</guid></item><item><title>[The Astrophysic] Spectral Shapes of Pair Annihilation Line Emission in Magnetar Giant Flares</title><link>https://iopscience.iop.org/article/10.3847/2041-8213/ae3289</link><description>We investigate the gamma-ray spectrum in the MeV range arising from electronâ€“positron pair annihilation in fireballs associated with magnetar giant flares (MGFs), motivated by the recent observation of a MeV gamma-ray line feature in a bright gamma-ray burst, GRB 221009A. We develop an analytic model of line emission, demonstrating that relativistic beaming results in a broadened power-law spectral feature with a photon index of âˆ’1. We then perform Monte Carlo radiative transfer simulations incorporating electronâ€“positron pair production, annihilation, and Compton scattering. The dependence of the emergent spectrum on the baryon loading is also examined, showing that a baryon-poor fireball is more favorable for the detection of MeV gamma rays. We further assess the detectability of the line component. The simulation results indicate that a power-law MeV component from the initial spike of a Galactic MGF could be observed with current instruments, such as Fermi/GBM, and will be well within the reach of upcoming MeV gamma-ray satellites, which are expected to detect photons from such events.</description><author>The Astrophysical Journal Letters - latest papers</author><pubDate>Wed, 14 Jan 2026 00:00:00 GMT</pubDate><guid isPermaLink="true">https://iopscience.iop.org/article/10.3847/2041-8213/ae3289</guid></item><item><title>[The Astrophysic] New Evidence for Extragalactic Einstein Probe Transients Associated with Long Gamma-Ray Bursts</title><link>https://iopscience.iop.org/article/10.3847/2041-8213/ae2012</link><description>The origin of extragalactic fast X-ray transients (EFXTs) remains a fundamental open question in high-energy astrophysics. The Einstein Probe (EP) mission provides a transformative opportunity to investigate their nature. While mounting observations of EP-discovered EFXTs (EP-EFXTs) suggest a possible connection to long gamma-ray bursts (lGRBs), an in-depth comparative analysis between them remains lacking. Here, we present a comparative analysis of their cosmic formation histories, revealing that EP-EFXTs and lGRBs share a similar evolutionary trendâ€”showing a marked decline at z &lt; 1.0 and a plateau beyond 1.0 &lt; z &lt; 5â€”that clearly distinguishes them from short GRBs. This result is derived from a rigorously selected sample of EP-EFXTs, using Lynden-Bellâ€™s câˆ’ method to reconstruct, for the first time, the luminosity function and formation rate of EP-EFXTs without any assumptions. Our findings provide independent evidence that EP-EFXTs and lGRBs may originate from a common progenitor channel.</description><author>The Astrophysical Journal Letters - latest papers</author><pubDate>Wed, 14 Jan 2026 00:00:00 GMT</pubDate><guid isPermaLink="true">https://iopscience.iop.org/article/10.3847/2041-8213/ae2012</guid></item><item><title>[astro-ph update] Exoplanet characterization with NASA's Habitable Worlds Observatory</title><link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2601.06233</link><description>arXiv:2601.06233v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: Exoplanet atmosphere characterization has seen revolutionary advances over the last few years, providing us with unique insights into atmospheric chemistry, dynamics and planet formation mechanisms. However, true solar system analog planets remain inaccessible. A major goal for exoplanet science over the coming decades is to observe, and characterize, temperate rocky planets and cool gas giants in orbit around solar-type stars, with the prospect of detecting signs of habitability or even life. Characterization and categorization of these planets relies on direct spectroscopic observations capable of identifying molecular species in their atmospheres; however, these observations represent a substantial engineering challenge due to the extreme contrast between a temperate, Earth-sized exoplanet and its parent star. NASA's next flagship mission, the Habitable Worlds Observatory (HWO) - planned for launch in the mid-2040s - will boast a coronagraphic instrument capable of reaching the needed 10$^{-10}$ contrast, on an ultrastable platform enabling long integration times to achieve the required signal to noise. HWO will cover near-ultraviolet to the near-infrared wavelengths, enabling detections of key biosignature molecules and habitability indicators such as ocean glint and a vegetation `red edge'. Via early involvement in this groundbreaking observatory, including a potential UK instrument contribution, the UK exoplanet community now has an important opportunity to influence the telescope's design. To maintain our international competitiveness, we must be at the forefront of observational campaigns with HWO when it eventually launches, and this comes with the need for parallel development in laboratory astrophysics and computational modelling. Maximising our exploitation of this transformative NASA mission requires consistent financial support in these areas across the next two decades.</description><author>astro-ph updates on arXiv.org</author><pubDate>Tue, 13 Jan 2026 05:00:00 GMT</pubDate><guid isPermaLink="true">oai:arXiv.org:2601.06233v1</guid></item><item><title>[astro-ph update] Spectral Signatures of Spinning Dust from Grain Ensembles in Diverse Environments: A Combined Theoretical and Observational Study</title><link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2601.06270</link><description>arXiv:2601.06270v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: Recent observations of anomalous microwave emission (AME) reveal spectral features that are not readily reproduced by spinning dust models, motivating further investigation. We examine how dust grain distributions and environmental parameters determine the peak frequency and spectral width of AME spectral energy distribution (SED). Using Monte Carlo sampling and global sensitivity analysis, we find that AME features are dominantly controlled by three parameters: grain size, shape, and a phase-dependent environmental parameter. We also quantify the effects of SED broadening from ensembles of these dominant parameters, finding that the level of tension with observations is strongly phase dependent: Molecular Cloud (MC) is fully consistent, Dark Cloud (DC) shows minor deviations, and HII regions exhibit significant offsets in peak frequency. This points to possible issues in phase-dependent AME extraction, interstellar medium (ISM) environment identification, or underlying theoretical tension. Ensemble variations in both grain size and environmental parameters are required to reproduce the observed spread in peak frequency and spectral width. We further propose moment expansion and emulation-based inference methods for future AME spectral fit and feature analysis.</description><author>astro-ph updates on arXiv.org</author><pubDate>Tue, 13 Jan 2026 05:00:00 GMT</pubDate><guid isPermaLink="true">oai:arXiv.org:2601.06270v1</guid></item><item><title>[astro-ph update] CAMELS Environments: The Impact of Local Neighbours on Galaxy Evolution across the SIMBA, IllustrisTNG, ASTRID, and Swift-EAGLE Simulations</title><link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2601.06290</link><description>arXiv:2601.06290v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: Internal feedback from massive stars and active galactic nuclei (AGN) play a key role in galaxy evolution, but external environmental effects can also strongly influence galaxies. We investigate the impact of environment on galaxy evolution, and its dependence on baryonic physics implementation, using Cosmology and Astrophysics with MachinE Learning Simulations (CAMELS) spanning a wide range of stellar and AGN feedback implementations in the SIMBA, IllustrisTNG, ASTRID, and Swift-EAGLE galaxy formation models. We show that satellite galaxies are significantly affected by the environment in all simulation models, with their gas fraction and star formation rate (SFR) suppressed in overdense regions compared to similar mass satellites in underdense environments at $z=0$. Central galaxies are less sensitive to environment but tend to show lower gas fraction and SFR in overdense regions at low stellar mass, transitioning to higher gas fraction and SFR for massive galaxies in higher-density environments. Halo baryon fraction ($f_{\rm B}$) and circumgalactic medium mass fraction ($f_{\rm CGM}$) at $z=0$ show clear environmental effects. In SIMBA, low-mass haloes in overdense regions have systematically lower $f_{\rm B}$ and $f_{\rm CGM}$ at fixed halo mass, while Swift-EAGLE haloes in overdense regions have systematically higher $f_{\rm B}$ and $f_{\rm CGM}$ across the full halo mass range, and IllustrisTNG and ASTRID show opposite trends at the low and high mass ends. Environmental effects can flip at higher redshift, with SFR and $f_{\rm B}$ increasing with local density in low-mass haloes before quenching at an increasing overdensity threshold. Our results demonstrate that the impact of environment on galaxy evolution depends significantly on galaxy formation model, and higher-density environments can either suppress or enhance star formation depending on galaxy mass and cosmic epoch.</description><author>astro-ph updates on arXiv.org</author><pubDate>Tue, 13 Jan 2026 05:00:00 GMT</pubDate><guid isPermaLink="true">oai:arXiv.org:2601.06290v1</guid></item><item><title>[astro-ph update] Collision between molecular clouds IV: The role of feedback and magnetic field in head on collisions</title><link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2601.06355</link><description>arXiv:2601.06355v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: We systematically investigate how cloud-cloud collisions influence star formation, emphasizing the roles of collision velocity, magnetic field orientation, and radiative feedback. Using the first cloud-cloud collision simulations that model individual star formation and accretion with all stellar feedback mechanisms, we explore the morphological evolution, star formation efficiency (SFE), fragmentation, stellar mass distribution, and feedback-driven gas dispersal. Our results show that cloud collisions substantially enhance the rate and timing of star formation compared to isolated scenarios, though the final SFE remains broadly similar across all setups. Lower collision velocities facilitate prolonged gravitational interaction and accumulation of gas, promoting sustained star formation characterized by elongated filamentary structures. Conversely, high-velocity collisions induce rapid gas compression and turbulent motions, leading to intense but transient episodes of star formation, which are curtailed by feedback-driven dispersal. The orientation of the magnetic field markedly affects collision outcomes. Parallel fields allow gas to collapse efficiently along magnetic lines, forming fewer but more massive stars. In contrast, perpendicular fields generate significant magnetic pressure, which stabilizes the shock-compressed gas and delays gravitational collapse, resulting in more distributed and less massive stellar fragments. Radiative feedback from massive stars consistently regulates star formation, halting further gas accretion at moderate efficiencies (10-15%) and initiating feedback-driven dispersal. Although the cloud dynamics vary significantly, the stellar mass function remains robust across scenarios-shaped modestly by magnetic orientation but only weakly influenced by collision velocity.</description><author>astro-ph updates on arXiv.org</author><pubDate>Tue, 13 Jan 2026 05:00:00 GMT</pubDate><guid isPermaLink="true">oai:arXiv.org:2601.06355v1</guid></item><item><title>[astro-ph update] Constraining Inflation Models with Spinning Voids</title><link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2601.06589</link><description>arXiv:2601.06589v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: We present a powerful new diagnostics by which the running of scalar spectral index of primordial density fluctuations can be tightly and independently constrained. This new diagnostics utilizes coherent rotation of void galaxies, which can be observed as redshift asymmetry in opposite sides dichotomized by the projected spin axes of hosting voids. Comparing the numerical results from the AbacusSummit of cosmological simulations, we derive a non-parametric model for the redshift asymmetry distribution of void galaxies, which turns out to be almost universally valid for a very broad range of cosmologies including dynamic dark energy models with time-dependent equation of states as well as the $\Lambda$CDM models with various initial conditions. We discover that the universality of this model breaks down only if the running of scalar spectral index deviates from zero, detecting a consistent trend that a more positive (negative) running yields a lower (higher) redshift asymmetry of voids than the model predictions. Given that non-standard inflations usually predict non-zero runnings of the spectral index and that the redshift asymmetry distribution of voids is a readily observable quantity, we conclude that this new diagnostics will pave another path toward understanding the true mechanism of inflation.</description><author>astro-ph updates on arXiv.org</author><pubDate>Tue, 13 Jan 2026 05:00:00 GMT</pubDate><guid isPermaLink="true">oai:arXiv.org:2601.06589v1</guid></item><item><title>[astro-ph update] Turbulent Properties of Interplanetary Coronal Mass Ejections Observed by Solar Orbiter in the Inner Heliosphere</title><link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2601.06904</link><description>arXiv:2601.06904v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: We investigate the turbulent properties of 12 interplanetary coronal mass ejections (ICMEs) observed by Solar Orbiter between 0.29 and 1.0 AU. We analyze fluctuation power, spectral indices, break scales, and correlations between magnetic and velocity fluctuations (v-b) to quantify differences between ICME substructures (sheath and magnetic ejecta (ME)) and the surrounding solar wind. The ICME sheath is consistently the most turbulent region at all distances. In the solar wind, Alfv\'enicity influences inertial-range scaling, resulting in either single power laws near f^-3/2 or f^-5/3, or a coexistence of both, whereas ICME substructures consistently exhibit Kolmogorov-like f^-5/3 spectra. Alfv\'enicity is reduced within ICMEs, particularly in the ejecta, indicating more balanced Alfv\'enic fluctuations than in the solar wind. Spectral breaks shift to higher frequencies in ICME regions, with average break frequencies of 0.53 +/- 0.35 Hz (solar wind), 1.87 +/- 1.46 Hz (sheath), and 1.46 +/- 1.28 Hz (ME), reflecting differences in underlying microphysical scales. Our findings highlight distinct turbulence regimes in ICMEs compared to the solar wind and support the use of fluctuation power, spectral breaks, and v-b correlations as effective diagnostics for identifying ICME boundaries.</description><author>astro-ph updates on arXiv.org</author><pubDate>Tue, 13 Jan 2026 05:00:00 GMT</pubDate><guid isPermaLink="true">oai:arXiv.org:2601.06904v1</guid></item><item><title>[astro-ph update] More power on large scales</title><link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2601.07106</link><description>arXiv:2601.07106v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: The high value of the cosmic microwave dipole may be telling us that dark matter is macroscopic rather than a fundamental particle. The possible presence of a significant dark matter component in the form of primordial black holes suggests that dark halo formation simulations should be commenced well before redshift z = 100. Unlike standard CDM candidates, PBHs behave as dense, non-relativistic matter from their inception in the radiation-dominated era. This allows them to seed gravitational potential wells and begin clustering earlier. We find that starting N-body simulations at redshifts even before matter-radiation equality yield galaxy bulk flow velocities that are systematically larger than those predicted by standard LCDM models. The early, high-mass concentrations established by PBHs lead to a more rapid and efficient gravitational acceleration of surrounding baryonic and dark matter, generating larger peculiar velocities that remain coherent over scales of hundreds of Mpc. Furthermore, a sub-population of PBHs in the 10^-20 to 10^-17 solar mass range would lose a non-negligible fraction of their mass via Hawking radiation over cosmological timescales. This evaporation process converts matter into radiation, so a time-varying matter density parameter, Omega_m', is introduced, which behaves like a boosted radiation term in the Friedmann equation. This dynamic term acts to reduce the Hubble tension. A higher effective Omega_r in the early universe reduces the sound horizon at the epoch of recombination. PBH mass loss also influences fits to the equation of state parameter, w, at low redshift. The naive N-body modelling presented here suggests investigation with tried and tested cosmology codes should be carried out, by introducing mass losing PBHs and starting the evolution as early as practicable.</description><author>astro-ph updates on arXiv.org</author><pubDate>Tue, 13 Jan 2026 05:00:00 GMT</pubDate><guid isPermaLink="true">oai:arXiv.org:2601.07106v1</guid></item><item><title>[astro-ph update] A Study Revealing Physical Attributes of Supernova Remnant in G321.3-3.9</title><link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2601.07170</link><description>arXiv:2601.07170v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: We present a radio analysis of the recently identified supernova remnant G321.3-3.9 using archival multi-wavelength data spanning 88-2304 MHz. The source exhibits an elliptical shell-like morphology (1.3 deg x 1.7 deg) and a relatively flat non-thermal spectral index of alpha = -0.40 +/- 0.03. The distance is estimated using both the Sigma-D relation (1.6-2.9 kpc) and tentative associations with HI structures, the latter suggesting a near-side solution of 2.5-3.3 kpc, though the physical connection remains uncertain.</description><author>astro-ph updates on arXiv.org</author><pubDate>Tue, 13 Jan 2026 05:00:00 GMT</pubDate><guid isPermaLink="true">oai:arXiv.org:2601.07170v1</guid></item><item><title>[astro-ph update] Does the radio-active phase of XTE~J1810$-$197 recur following the same evolutionary pattern?</title><link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2601.07173</link><description>arXiv:2601.07173v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: Magnetars are the most strongly magnetized compact objects known in the Universe and are regarded as one of the primary engines powering a variety of enigmatic, high-energy transients. However, our understanding of magnetars remains highly limited, constrained by observational sample size and radiative variability. XTE~J1810$-$197, which re-entered a radio-active phase in 2018, is one of only six known radio-pulsating magnetars. Leveraging the distinctive capability for simultaneous dual-frequency observations, we utilized the Shanghai Tianma Radio Telescope (TMRT) to monitor this magnetar continuously at both 2.25 and 8.60~GHz, capturing its entire evolution from radio activation to quenching. This enabled precise characterization of the evolution in its integrated profile, spin frequency, flux density, and spectral index ($\alpha$, defined by $S \propto f^{\alpha}$). The first time derivative of its spin frequency $\dot{\nu}$ passed through four distinct phases -- rapid decrease, violent oscillation, steady decline, and stable recovery -- before returning to its pre-outburst value concomitant with the cessation of radio emission. Remarkably, both the amplitudes and the characteristic time-scales of these $\dot{\nu}$ variations match those observed during the previous outburst that began in 2003, providing the first demonstration that post-outburst rotational evolution and radiative behavior in a magnetar are repeatable. A twisted-magnetosphere model can qualitatively account for this repeatability as well as for the progressive narrowing and abrupt disappearance of the radio pulse radiation, thereby receiving strong observational support.</description><author>astro-ph updates on arXiv.org</author><pubDate>Tue, 13 Jan 2026 05:00:00 GMT</pubDate><guid isPermaLink="true">oai:arXiv.org:2601.07173v1</guid></item><item><title>[astro-ph update] Photometric Redshift Estimation Using Scaled Ensemble Learning</title><link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2601.07292</link><description>arXiv:2601.07292v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: The development of the state-of-the-art telescopic systems capable of performing expansive sky surveys such as the Sloan Digital Sky Survey, Euclid, and the Rubin Observatory's Legacy Survey of Space and Time (LSST) has significantly advanced efforts to refine cosmological models. These advances offer deeper insight into persistent challenges in astrophysics and our understanding of the Universe's evolution. A critical component of this progress is the reliable estimation of photometric redshifts (Pz). To improve the precision and efficiency of such estimations, the application of machine learning (ML) techniques to large-scale astronomical datasets has become essential. This study presents a new ensemble-based ML framework aimed at predicting Pz for faint galaxies and higher redshift ranges, relying solely on optical (grizy) photometric data. The proposed architecture integrates several learning algorithms, including gradient boosting machine, extreme gradient boosting, k-nearest neighbors, and artificial neural networks, within a scaled ensemble structure. By using bagged input data, the ensemble approach delivers improved predictive performance compared to stand-alone models. The framework demonstrates consistent accuracy in estimating redshifts, maintaining strong performance up to z ~ 4. The model is validated using publicly available data from the Hyper Suprime-Cam Strategic Survey Program by the Subaru Telescope. Our results show marked improvements in the precision and reliability of Pz estimation. Furthermore, this approach closely adheres to-and in certain instances exceeds-the benchmarks specified in the LSST Science Requirements Document. Evaluation metrics include catastrophic outlier, bias, and rms.</description><author>astro-ph updates on arXiv.org</author><pubDate>Tue, 13 Jan 2026 05:00:00 GMT</pubDate><guid isPermaLink="true">oai:arXiv.org:2601.07292v1</guid></item><item><title>[astro-ph update] Modified Gravity and the Origin of the Excess Radio Galaxy Number-Count Dipole</title><link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2601.07487</link><description>arXiv:2601.07487v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: Recent analyses of wide-area radio-galaxy surveys have reported a statistically significant excess in the cosmic number-count dipole, with an amplitude exceeding the purely kinematic expectation of the standard $\Lambda$CDM model by a factor of $\sim 3$--$4$, quoted at a significance level of up to $5.4\sigma$. While residual observational systematics and local-structure effects cannot be definitively excluded, this result motivates the exploration of alternative physical interpretations beyond the minimal $\Lambda$CDM framework. We investigate whether Scalar--Tensor--Vector Gravity (STVG-MOG) can provide a consistent explanation for an enhanced large-scale anisotropic dipole without violating existing constraints from early-universe cosmology, the cosmic microwave background (CMB) dipole, galaxy dynamics, weak lensing, or the observed late-time matter power spectrum. The radio number-count dipole probes ultra-large-scale, anisotropic structure and coherent gravitational response, rather than virialized dynamics or linear growth alone. In STVG-MOG, a scale- and time-dependent effective gravitational coupling preserves standard cosmological evolution at early times and on small to intermediate scales, while amplifying gravitational response on gigaparsec scales. This scale-selective enhancement can increase the large-scale structure contribution to the radio dipole without overproducing power on smaller scales. If the observed dipole excess reflects a physical cosmological signal rather than residual systematics, STVG-MOG offers a viable and testable alternative interpretation. It is demonstrated that the radio dipole anomaly provides a novel probe of gravitational physics on the largest observable scales.</description><author>astro-ph updates on arXiv.org</author><pubDate>Tue, 13 Jan 2026 05:00:00 GMT</pubDate><guid isPermaLink="true">oai:arXiv.org:2601.07487v1</guid></item><item><title>[astro-ph update] Galaxy Mergers in UNIONS -- II: Predicting Timescales in the Post-Merger Regime</title><link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2601.07604</link><description>arXiv:2601.07604v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: Galaxy mergers are critical events that influence galaxy evolution by driving processes such as enhanced star formation, quenching, and active galactic nucleus (AGN) activity. However, constraining the timescales over which these processes occur in the post-merger phase has remained a significant challenge. This study extends the MUlti-Model Merger Identifier (\textsc{Mummi}) framework to predict post-merger timescales ($T_{PM}$) for galaxies, leveraging machine learning models trained on realism-enhanced mock observations derived from the IllustrisTNG simulations. By classifying post-merger galaxies into four temporal bins spanning 0 to 1.76 Gyr after coalescence, \textsc{Mummi} achieves time classification accuracies exceeding 70 per cent. We apply this framework to the Ultraviolet Near Infrared Optical Northern Survey (UNIONS), yielding a catalog of 8,716 post-merger galaxies with $T_{PM}$ predictions and stellar masses $\log(M_*/M_\odot) \geq 10$ at redshifts 0.03 &lt; z &lt; 0.3. These results provide a robust methodology to connect galaxy interaction timescales with physical processes, enabling detailed studies of galaxy evolution in the post-merger regime.</description><author>astro-ph updates on arXiv.org</author><pubDate>Tue, 13 Jan 2026 05:00:00 GMT</pubDate><guid isPermaLink="true">oai:arXiv.org:2601.07604v1</guid></item><item><title>[astro-ph update] Brightest GRB flare observed in GRB 221009A: bridge the last gap between flare and prompt emission in GRB</title><link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2601.07688</link><description>arXiv:2601.07688v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: Flares are usually observed during the afterglow phase of Gamma-Ray Bursts (GRBs) in soft X-ray, optical and radio bands, but rarely in gamma-ray band. Despite the extraordinary brightness, GECAM-C has accurately measured both the bright prompt emission and flare emission of GRB 221009A without instrumental effects, offering a good opportunity to study the relation between them. In this work, we present a comprehensive analysis of flare emission of GRB 221009A, which is composed of a series of flares. Among them, we identify an exceptionally bright flare with a record-breaking isotropic energy $E_{\rm iso} = 1.82 \times 10^{53}$ erg of GRB flares. It exhibits the highest peak energy ever detected in GRB flares, $E_{\rm peak} \sim 300$ keV, making it a genuine gamma-ray flare. It also shows rapid rise and decay timescales, significantly shorter than those of typical X-ray flares observed in soft X-ray or optical band, but comparable to those observed in prompt emissions. Despite these exceptional properties, the flare shares several common properties with typical GRB flares. We note that this is the first observation of a GRB flare in the keV-MeV band with sufficiently high temporal resolution and high statistics, which bridges the last gap between prompt emission and flare.</description><author>astro-ph updates on arXiv.org</author><pubDate>Tue, 13 Jan 2026 05:00:00 GMT</pubDate><guid isPermaLink="true">oai:arXiv.org:2601.07688v1</guid></item><item><title>[astro-ph update] A COLIBRI Photometric Study of SN 2025bvm: A Normal, Slowly Declining Type Ia Supernova</title><link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2601.07745</link><description>arXiv:2601.07745v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: We present 121 days of multi-band (\Bband, \gband, \rband, \iband) optical photometry of the Type Ia supernova SN 2025bvm, obtained with the COLIBRI telescope at OAN-SPM. The light curves show a photometric decline of $\Delta m_{15}(B) = 0.867 \pm 0.051$~mag, characteristic of a slow-declining Type Ia supernova. After correcting for host galaxy extinction ($E(B-V)_{host} = 0.308 \pm 0.030$~mag) and adopting a distance of 70~Mpc, we derive a peak absolute magnitude of $M_B = -19.13 \pm 0.40$~mag. This luminosity is fully consistent with its slow decline rate, placing SN 2025bvm within the population of normal Type Ia supernovae. We conclude that SN 2025bvm is a normal Type Ia supernova, whose photometric properties, such as a slow late-time decline and a prominent \iband-band secondary maximum, suggest an explosion that resulted in a particularly massive ejecta.</description><author>astro-ph updates on arXiv.org</author><pubDate>Tue, 13 Jan 2026 05:00:00 GMT</pubDate><guid isPermaLink="true">oai:arXiv.org:2601.07745v1</guid></item><item><title>[astro-ph update] Cosmoglobe DR2. IV. Modelling starlight in DIRBE with Gaia and WISE</title><link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2601.07831</link><description>arXiv:2601.07831v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: We present a model of starlight emission in the Diffuse Infrared Background Explorer (DIRBE) data between 1.25 and 25$\,\mu$m based on \textit{Gaia} and WISE measurements. We include two classes of compact objects, namely bright stars with individual spectral energy densities (SEDs) measured by \textit{Gaia}, and a combined diffuse background of dim point source emission. Of the 424\ 829 bright sources that we fit, the number of stars with a flux density detected by WISE at Galactic latitudes $|b|&gt;20^{\circ}$ at more than $5\,\sigma$ is 94\,680, for an average of 1.36~stars per DIRBE beam area. For each star, we adopt physical parameters ($T_{\mathrm{eff}}$, $\log g$, and [M/H]) from \textit{Gaia}; use these to identify a best-fit effective SED with the PHOENIX stellar model library; convolve with the respective DIRBE bandpass; and fit an overall free amplitude per star within the Bayesian end-to-end \texttt{Cosmoglobe} DR2 framework. The contributions from faint sources are accounted for by coadding all 710\ 825\ 587 WISE sources not included as bright stars, and fit one single overall amplitude per DIRBE band. Based on this model we find that total star emission accounts for 91\,\% of the observed flux density at 2.2\,$\mu$m; 54\,\% at 4.9$\,\mu$m; and 1\,\% at 25\,$\mu$m. As shown in companion papers, this new model is sufficiently accurate to support high-precision measurements of both the Cosmic Infrared Background monopole and zodiacal light emission in the three highest DIRBE frequencies.</description><author>astro-ph updates on arXiv.org</author><pubDate>Tue, 13 Jan 2026 05:00:00 GMT</pubDate><guid isPermaLink="true">oai:arXiv.org:2601.07831v1</guid></item><item><title>[astro-ph update] Strong Einstein-Hilbert Gravity Inflation and ACT Phenomenology</title><link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2601.06946</link><description>arXiv:2601.06946v1 Announce Type: cross 
Abstract: In this work we study rescaled effective single scalar field theories, and we confront these with the ACT constraint on the spectral index of the scalar primordial perturbations and the updated BICEP/Planck constraint on the tensor-to-scalar ratio. Rescaled scalar theories of gravity may be the result of an effective $f(R,\phi)$ gravity at strong curvature regimes, which may result on a rescaling of the Einstein-Hilbert term of the form $\sim \alpha R$. It turns out that canonical scalar field theories with stronger gravity compared to standard Einstein-Hilbert gravity can be compatible with the ACT and updated Planck/BICEP constraints, with stronger gravity meaning that the rescaling parameter $\alpha$ takes values smaller than unity.</description><author>astro-ph updates on arXiv.org</author><pubDate>Tue, 13 Jan 2026 05:00:00 GMT</pubDate><guid isPermaLink="true">oai:arXiv.org:2601.06946v1</guid></item><item><title>[astro-ph update] Viable f(R) Scenarios Unifying Inflation with Realistic Dynamical Dark Energy</title><link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2601.06949</link><description>arXiv:2601.06949v1 Announce Type: cross 
Abstract: Two $F(R)$ gravity models are tested on the basis of their viability during all stages of cosmological evolution. It is shown that these models can describe both the early-time inflationary epoch and the dark energy epoch. The models are confronted with the latest observational data, including the Pantheon+ catalogue with Type Ia supernovae, the Dark Energy Spectroscopic Instrument measurements of baryon acoustic oscillations, the Hubble parameter estimations and data from cosmic microwave background radiation. Investigation of the viability conditions for these models, in particular, the condition $\frac{dF}{dR}&gt;0$ required a deep analysis. Both models appeared to be viable during the early-time era, but for the late-time evolution the viability conditions are not fulfilled in definite domains in the parameter spaces of these models. However the best fitted parameters, determined in confrontation with the mentioned observational data, lie far from the forbidden domains for both models. These $F(R)$ gravity models describe the observations with the large advantage over the $\Lambda$-Cold-Dark-Matter model, not only in $\chi^2$ statistics, but also with Akaike and Bayesian information criteria. This success of the two $F(R)$ gravity scenarios is connected with their capability to mimic dynamical dark energy, similarly to models with variable equation of state, that is necessary for describing the latest Pantheon+ and DESI observational data.</description><author>astro-ph updates on arXiv.org</author><pubDate>Tue, 13 Jan 2026 05:00:00 GMT</pubDate><guid isPermaLink="true">oai:arXiv.org:2601.06949v1</guid></item><item><title>[astro-ph update] Confronting Mukhanov Parametrization of Inflationary Equation-of-State with ACT-DR6</title><link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2507.05648</link><description>arXiv:2507.05648v2 Announce Type: replace 
Abstract: We provide a simple yet effective semi-analytical approach to confront Mukhanov Parametrization of inflationary equation-of-state, $1+\omega =\frac{\beta}{({N}+1)^\alpha}$, with the latest ACT-DR6 data employing Hamilton-Jacobi formulation. We find that equation-of-state formalism comes up with excellent fit to the latest data. In the process we are also able to put stringent constraint on the two model parameters. In order to get the bounds of $\alpha$ and $\beta$ we have also made use of the recent finding $r&lt;0.032$. We have further utilized results from the joint analysis of ACT-DR6, Planck-2018 and DESI-Y1 data to find the observationally viable region for $\alpha$ and $\beta$. We have also employed the predictions on primordial gravity waves from forthcoming CMB missions in the likes of CMB-S4 and LiteBIRD along with results from the combination of ACT-DR6, Planck-2018 and DESI-Y1 data to further restrict the model parameters. We find that detection of gravity waves would help us narrow the viable parameter space for Mukhanov parametrization. But in the absence of detection of primordial gravity waves signal by those CMB missions parameter space is reduced significantly for $\beta$, while the range for $\alpha$ is slightly increased. In addition we observe that, $\alpha$ is primarily dependent on the observationally viable range for scalar spectral index while other model parameter $\beta$ is resting heavily on the restriction upon the amplitude of primordial gravity waves. We find that equation-of-state formalism has a wide range of parameter values consistent with recent observational data set along with futuristic CMB missions in the likes of CMB-S4 and LiteBIRD.</description><author>astro-ph updates on arXiv.org</author><pubDate>Tue, 13 Jan 2026 05:00:00 GMT</pubDate><guid isPermaLink="true">oai:arXiv.org:2507.05648v2</guid></item><item><title>[astro-ph update] Measuring the Central Dark Mass in NGC 4258 with JWST/NIRSpec Stellar Kinematics</title><link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2509.20519</link><description>arXiv:2509.20519v2 Announce Type: replace 
Abstract: We present a new stellar dynamical measurement of the supermassive black hole (SMBH) mass in the nearby spiral galaxy NGC 4258, a critical benchmark for extragalactic mass measurements. We use archival JWST/NIRSpec IFU data (G235H/F170LP grating) to extract high-resolution two-dimensional stellar kinematics from the CO bandhead absorption features within the central $3'' \times 3''$. We extract the stellar kinematics after correcting for instrumental artifacts and separating the stellar light from the non-thermal AGN continuum. We employ Jeans Anisotropic Models (JAM) to fit the observed kinematics, exploring a grid of 12 models to systematically test the impact of different assumptions for the point-spread function, stellar mass-to-light ratio ($M/L$) profile, and orbital anisotropy. All 12 models provide broadly acceptable fits, albeit with minor differences. The ensemble median and 68% (1$\sigma$) bootstrap confidence intervals of our 12 models yield a black hole mass of $M_{\rm BH} = (4.08^{+0.19}_{-0.33}) \times 10^7$ M$_\odot$. This paper showcases the utility of using the full model ensemble to robustly account for systematic uncertainties, rather than relying on formal errors from a single preferred model, as has been common practice. Our result is just 5% larger than, and consistent with, the benchmark SMBH mass derived from water maser dynamics, validating the use of NIRSpec stellar kinematics for robust SMBH mass determination. Our analysis demonstrates JWST's capability to resolve the SMBH's sphere of influence and deliver precise dynamical masses, even in the presence of significant AGN continuum emission.</description><author>astro-ph updates on arXiv.org</author><pubDate>Tue, 13 Jan 2026 05:00:00 GMT</pubDate><guid isPermaLink="true">oai:arXiv.org:2509.20519v2</guid></item><item><title>[astro-ph update] Implications of Joint Spectral Analysis of Gamma-Ray Bursts detected by Fermi Large Area Telescope and Gamma-ray Burst Monitor on Phenomenological Correlations</title><link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2510.16475</link><description>arXiv:2510.16475v2 Announce Type: replace 
Abstract: Gamma-ray bursts (GRBs) have emerged as powerful cosmological probes for exploring the distant Universe, owing to their immense luminosities and detectability at high redshifts. Several empirical correlations have been established, particularly involving their energy properties. This work aims to enhance the precision of these correlations through joint spectral analysis, focusing on reducing uncertainties in both the spectral indices and the peak energy ($E_{\rm p}$) derived from spectral fitting. We extend previous studies using both traditional and novel spectral models, utilizing a sample of 37 GRBs observed by the Fermi Gamma-ray Burst Monitor (GBM) and Large Area Telescope (LAT), incorporating the LAT Low-Energy (LLE) technique, over the period 2008-2024. Our analysis compares results from joint fits (GBM-LAT-LLE) against those from GBM-only fits. The study focuses on fitting time-integrated ${\rm T}_{90}$ and peak flux in the rest frame. Among the observable phenomenological correlations, we revisit the Amati and Yonetoku relations: the Amati relation links the intrinsic peak energy ($E_{i,\rm p}$) to the total isotropic energy ($E_{\rm iso}$) emitted during ${\rm T}_{90}$, while the Yonetoku relation connects $E_{i,\rm p}$ to the isotropic luminosity ($L_{\rm iso}$). Refining these correlations aims to deepen our understanding of GRB energetics and improve the precision of cosmological parameter estimates derived from GRB observations.</description><author>astro-ph updates on arXiv.org</author><pubDate>Tue, 13 Jan 2026 05:00:00 GMT</pubDate><guid isPermaLink="true">oai:arXiv.org:2510.16475v2</guid></item><item><title>[astro-ph update] Stellar Wind-Blown Bubbles as Environments for Late-Time Rebrightening of Gamma-Ray Burst Afterglows</title><link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2510.22891</link><description>arXiv:2510.22891v2 Announce Type: replace 
Abstract: We presented the multi-wavelength afterglow fitting results for three events that exhibit late afterglow rebrightening behavior: EP240414a ($z=0.401$), GRB 240529A ($z=2.695$), and GRB 240218A ($z=6.782$), which span a broad range of redshifts, from the local to the high-redshift universe.We prove that the peculiar afterglow light curves of three bursts can be well fitted by structured jets propagated in free-to-shocked stellar wind environment of stellar wind blown bubbles. This scenario offers a self-consistent explanation for the observed subclass of afterglows that exhibit rebrightening that is characterized by steep rises and rapid decays. It also provides a unified solution for such events and offers pathways to study both the jet generation mechanism and the propagation process of jets through the envelope of the progenitor. This study reveals that the structured jets produced by such events exhibit a narrow jet core and a steep angle-dependent energy decay index, suggesting highly magnetized jets. The derived transition radii from free stellar winds to shocked stellar winds for all three events are smaller than 0.5 pc, with statistical analysis of similar events indicating a median value of 0.1 pc, which conflicts with numerical simulation results. We anticipate that future observations by EP and SVOM missions will enhance the understanding of analogous events and further reveal information about progenitors and their circum-environments.</description><author>astro-ph updates on arXiv.org</author><pubDate>Tue, 13 Jan 2026 05:00:00 GMT</pubDate><guid isPermaLink="true">oai:arXiv.org:2510.22891v2</guid></item><item><title>[astro-ph update] Sound waves from primordial black hole formations</title><link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2504.12243</link><description>arXiv:2504.12243v3 Announce Type: replace-cross 
Abstract: We present a numerical investigation of primordial black hole (PBH) formation from super-horizon curvature perturbations and the subsequent generation and propagation of sound waves, which can serve as a new source of stochastic gravitational wave backgrounds (SGWBs) presented in a companion letter. Using the Misner-Sharp formalism with an excision technique, our simulations extend to significantly later times than previous work and indicate that the near-critical perturbations produce a distinct compression wave featuring both overdense and underdense shells, while significantly supercritical perturbations yield only an underdense shell. We also show that a softer equation of state suppresses the formation of compression waves. Furthermore, the comoving thickness of sound shells remains nearly constant during propagation and scales with the Hubble radius at horizon re-entry, thereby serving as a key link between the gravitational-wave peak frequency and PBH mass in the companion letter. These results offer new insights into the dynamics of PBH formation and suggest potential observational signatures of PBHs in the gravitational wave (GW) spectrum from associated sound waves.</description><author>astro-ph updates on arXiv.org</author><pubDate>Tue, 13 Jan 2026 05:00:00 GMT</pubDate><guid isPermaLink="true">oai:arXiv.org:2504.12243v3</guid></item><item><title>[astro-ph update] Machine learning for radiative hydrodynamics in astrophysics</title><link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2601.05155</link><description>arXiv:2601.05155v2 Announce Type: replace-cross 
Abstract: Radiation hydrodynamics describes the interaction between high-temperature hypersonic plasmas and the radiation they emit or absorb, a coupling that plays a central role in many astrophysical phenomena related to accretion and ejection processes. The HADES code was developed to model such systems by coupling hydrodynamics with M1-gray or M1-multigroup radiative transfer models, which are well suited to optically intermediate media.
  Despite its accuracy, radiation hydrodynamics simulations remain extremely demanding in terms of computational cost. Two main limitations are responsible for this. First, the M1-multigroup model relies on a closure relation with no analytic expression, requiring expensive numerical evaluations. Second, the Courant-Friedrichs-Lewy condition strongly restricts the time step of the explicit schemes used in HADES. To overcome these difficulties, two complementary Artificial Intelligence based strategies were developed in this thesis.
  The first approach consists in training a Multi-Layer Perceptron to approximate the M1-multigroup closure relation. This method achieves excellent accuracy while reducing the computational cost by a factor of 3000, making it the most efficient approach currently available for this task. This performance gain enables high-fidelity simulations of radiative shocks, in which radiation directly influences the shock structure. In particular, increasing spectral resolution slows down the shock and enlarges the radiative precursor.
  The second approach explores the use of Physics-Informed Neural Networks to directly solve the radiation hydrodynamics equations and extrapolate simulations beyond their initial time range. Tests on purely hydrodynamic shocks show accurate handling of discontinuities, but application to radiative shocks remains challenging and requires further investigation.</description><author>astro-ph updates on arXiv.org</author><pubDate>Tue, 13 Jan 2026 05:00:00 GMT</pubDate><guid isPermaLink="true">oai:arXiv.org:2601.05155v2</guid></item><item><title>[The Astrophysic] Bistability, Oscillations, and Multistability on Hycean Planets</title><link>https://iopscience.iop.org/article/10.3847/1538-4357/ae18d7</link><description>Hycean planets are hypothetical exoplanets characterized by H2O oceans and H2-rich atmospheres. These planets are high-priority targets for biosignature searches, as they combine abundant surface liquid water with easy-to-characterize H2-rich atmospheres. Perhaps their most unusual climate feature is convective inhibition, which can dramatically alter a planetâ€™s temperature structure. However, so far, hycean planets have mostly been investigated using 1D models that do not account for convective inhibition, and its effects are still poorly understood. This work develops pen-and-paper theory to analyze the effects of moist convective inhibition on hycean planets. The theory is tested and verified against a 1D radiativeâ€“convective model. We show that hycean planets near the onset of convective inhibition can exhibit either bistability or oscillations, due to the inhibition layerâ€™s trapping of heat and moisture. Meanwhile, hot hycean planets exhibit multistability, in which the inhibition layer and surface climate show multiple stable equilibria due to the lack of constraints on the water cycle inside the inhibition layer. The water cycle inside the inhibition layer is influenced by numerous processes that are challenging to resolve in 1D, including turbulent diffusion, convective overshoot, and large-scale circulations. Our results demonstrate that hycean planets have unexpectedly rich climate dynamics. Meanwhile, previous claims about hycean planets should be treated with caution until confirmed with more self-consistent 1D and 3D models; this includes the claim that K2-18b might be habitable, as well as the proposal to infer H2O oceans on sub-Neptunes from JWST measurements of chemical species in their upper atmospheres.</description><author>The Astrophysical Journal - latest papers</author><pubDate>Tue, 13 Jan 2026 00:00:00 GMT</pubDate><guid isPermaLink="true">https://iopscience.iop.org/article/10.3847/1538-4357/ae18d7</guid></item><item><title>[The Astrophysic] The Relation between AGN and Host Galaxy Properties in the JWST Era. II. The Merger-driven Evolution of Seyferts at Cosmic Noon</title><link>https://iopscience.iop.org/article/10.3847/1538-4357/ae1ef8</link><description>In Paper I, we exploited the unsurpassed resolution and depth of JWST/NIRCam imagery to investigate the relationship between active galactic nuclei (AGN) and host-galaxy properties in the JWST era, finding a correlation between the level of spatial disturbance (as measured by shape asymmetry, AS) and obscuration (NH). Here in Paper II, we report an expansion of our X-ray and infrared analysis of Seyfert-luminosity host galaxies with four additional metrics to the single-metric morphology analysis of Paper I, as well as new samples of inactive control galaxies. This expanded study of one of the largest and most complete, multiwavelength samples of AGN detected at 0.6 &lt; z &lt; 3.8 in the GOODS-South and -North fields, confirms that mergers surprisingly play a significant role in obscured, subquasar AGN host galaxies. Additionally, the pattern of morphological disturbances observed amongst the X-ray- and mid-IR-selected AGN suggests that these represent different phases of AGN evolution tied to a major-merger timeline, as opposed to distinct populations of AGN. These results indicate that mergers are important in triggering subquasar AGN at these redshifts.</description><author>The Astrophysical Journal - latest papers</author><pubDate>Tue, 13 Jan 2026 00:00:00 GMT</pubDate><guid isPermaLink="true">https://iopscience.iop.org/article/10.3847/1538-4357/ae1ef8</guid></item><item><title>[The Astrophysic] Characterizing Supernova Host Galaxies with FrankenBlast: A Scalable Tool for Transient Host Galaxy Association, Photometry, and Stellar Population Modeling</title><link>https://iopscience.iop.org/article/10.3847/1538-4357/ae247b</link><description>We present FrankenBlast, a customized and improved version of the Blast web application. FrankenBlast associates transients to their host galaxies, performs host photometry, and runs a innovative spectral energy distribution fitting code to constrain host stellar population propertiesâ€”all within minutes per object. We test FrankenBlast on 14,432 supernovae (SNe), â‰ˆhalf of which are spectroscopically classified, and are able to constrain host properties for 9262 events. When contrasting the host stellar masses (M*), specific star formation rates (sSFR), and host dust extinction (AV) between spectroscopically and photometrically classified SNe Ia, Ib/c, II, and IIn, we determine that deviations in these distributions are primarily due to misclassified events contaminating the photometrically classified sample. We further show that the higher redshifts of the photometrically classified sample also force their M* and sSFR distributions to deviate from those of the spectroscopically classified sample, as these properties are redshift-dependent. We compare host properties between spectroscopically classified SN populations and determine if they primarily trace M* or SFR. We find that all SN populations seem to both depend on M* and SFR, with SNe II and IIn somewhat more SFR-dependent than SNe Ia and Ib/c, and SNe Ia more M*-dependent than all other classes. We find the difference in the SNe Ib/c and II hosts to be the most intriguing and speculate that SNe Ib/c must be more dependent on higher M* and more evolved environments for the right conditions for progenitor formation. All data products and FrankenBlast are publicly available, along with a developing FrankenBlast version intended for Rubin Observatory science products.</description><author>The Astrophysical Journal - latest papers</author><pubDate>Tue, 13 Jan 2026 00:00:00 GMT</pubDate><guid isPermaLink="true">https://iopscience.iop.org/article/10.3847/1538-4357/ae247b</guid></item><item><title>[The Astrophysic] Polarization Angle Orthogonal Jumps in Fast Radio Bursts</title><link>https://iopscience.iop.org/article/10.3847/1538-4357/ae285e</link><description>Recently, polarization angle (PA) orthogonal jumps over millisecond timescales were discovered from three bursts of the repeating fast radio burst source FRB 20201124A by the FAST telescope. In general, PA jumps can arise from the coherent or incoherent superposition of two electromagnetic waves, with the total polarization fraction remaining constant in the former and not in the latter. The observations seem to be more consistent with incoherent superposition. The amplitudes of the two orthogonal modes are required to be comparable when jumps occur. We provide general constraints on FRB emission and propagation mechanisms based on the data. Physically, it is difficult to produce PA jumps through switching the dominance of the two orthogonal modes within millisecond timescales, and a geometric effect due to rotation of the source is more plausible. This requires that the emission region be within the magnetosphere of a spinning central engine, likely a magnetar. The two orthogonal modes in different directions can arise when the rotation of the source brings two independent emission regions with different dominant modes successively into the line of sight, due to either intrinsic radiation mechanisms or the O-mode undergoing a delayed transparency because of the AlfvÃ©nâ€“O-mode conversion. Splitting of emission directions for the two modes due to plasma birefringence is not easy to achieve when the plasma is moving relativistically. For intrinsic radiation mechanisms, curvature radiation always predicts âˆ£EX/EOâˆ£ â‰³ 1, and it is difficult to produce jumps; whereas inverse Compton scattering can achieve the conversion amplitude ratio âˆ£EX/EOâˆ£ = 1 to allow jumps to occur under special geometric configurations.</description><author>The Astrophysical Journal - latest papers</author><pubDate>Tue, 13 Jan 2026 00:00:00 GMT</pubDate><guid isPermaLink="true">https://iopscience.iop.org/article/10.3847/1538-4357/ae285e</guid></item><item><title>[The Astrophysic] Signatures of Magnetic Flux Expulsion from Neutron Star Cores</title><link>https://iopscience.iop.org/article/10.3847/2041-8213/ae31f5</link><description>Shortly after a neutron star is born, the protons in its core begin to form a superconductor. In terrestrial materials, the hallmark of superconductivity is an associated expulsion of magnetic flux, but whether this expulsion process can be effective in neutron stars remains an open questionâ€”one with major implications for the phenomenology of pulsars and magnetars. Earlier theoretical arguments suggested flux must be trapped within the core, yet models of magnetars rely on it being expelled from the core and confined to the crust, where it can evolve on kiloyear timescales. We show that if expulsion is not complete, a qualitatively new evolutionary branch for neutron stars arises, which can account for the properties of newly discovered long-period radio transients and fast radio bursts in older environments. One recently proposed model that could create such field topologies has additional implications for gravitational-wave emission and predicts a characteristic energy release that, if observed, will corroborate the role of reconnection at the onset of superconductivity and can constrain the superconducting proton gap.</description><author>The Astrophysical Journal Letters - latest papers</author><pubDate>Tue, 13 Jan 2026 00:00:00 GMT</pubDate><guid isPermaLink="true">https://iopscience.iop.org/article/10.3847/2041-8213/ae31f5</guid></item><item><title>[The Astrophysic] Connecting Environment, Star Formation History, and Morphology of Massive Quiescent Galaxies at 3 &lt; z &lt; 4 with JWST</title><link>https://iopscience.iop.org/article/10.3847/1538-4357/ae0a18</link><description>We present the morphological properties of 17 spectroscopically confirmed massive quiescent galaxies ( ) at 3.0 &lt; z &lt; 4.3, observed with JWST/NIRSpec and NIRCam. Using SÃ©rsic profile fits to F277W and F444W imaging, we derive the sizeâ€“mass relation and find typical sizes of âˆ¼0.6â€“0.8 kpc at M* = 5 Ã— 1010MâŠ™, consistent with âˆ¼7Ã— growth from z âˆ¼ 4 to the present, including âˆ¼2Ã— by z âˆ¼ 2. We find tentative evidence that formation history and morphology jointly influence galaxy sizes: late-forming bulge-dominated galaxies appear more compact by âˆ¼0.2â€“0.3 dex relative to the expected relation, while late-forming disk-dominated galaxies are larger. Using a Random Forest regressor, we identify local environmental density, quantified by from the three nearest neighbors, as the strongest predictor of bulge-to-total ratio (B/T), which spans 0.25â€“1. In the IllustrisTNG simulation, the ex situ stellar mass fraction (f*,ex situ)â€”a proxy for mergersâ€”is instead the dominant predictor of B/T. Galaxies with high B/T in dense environments show bursty star formation and short quenching timescales (â‰²0.4 Gyr), consistent with bulge growth through merger-driven starbursts; in simulations, such systems exhibit elevated ex situ fractions (âˆ¼20%â€“30%). In contrast, some high-B/T galaxies in intermediate-density environments have low ex situ fractions, suggesting that additional processesâ€”such as violent disk instabilitiesâ€”also contribute. These results point to multiple bulge growth pathways at high redshift, unified by rapid gas accretion, central starbursts, and active galactic nucleus feedback, as predicted by cosmological simulations.</description><author>The Astrophysical Journal - latest papers</author><pubDate>Mon, 12 Jan 2026 00:00:00 GMT</pubDate><guid isPermaLink="true">https://iopscience.iop.org/article/10.3847/1538-4357/ae0a18</guid></item><item><title>[The Astrophysic] AGN STORM 2. XI. Spectroscopic Reverberation Mapping of the Hot Dust in Mrk 817</title><link>https://iopscience.iop.org/article/10.3847/1538-4357/ae17cd</link><description>The AGN Space Telescope and Optical Reverberation Mapping (STORM) 2 campaign targeted Mrk 817 with intensive multiwavelength monitoring and found its soft X-ray emission to be strongly absorbed. We present results from 157 near-IR spectra with an average cadence of a few days. Whereas the hot dust reverberation signal as tracked by the continuum flux does not have a clear response, we recover a dust reverberation radius of âˆ¼90 lt-days from the blackbody dust temperature light curve. This radius is consistent with previous photometric reverberation mapping results when Mrk 817 was in an unobscured state. The heating/cooling process we observe indicates that the inner limit of the dusty torus is set by a process other than sublimation, rendering it a luminosity-invariant â€œdusty wallâ€ of a carbonaceous composition. Assuming thermal equilibrium for dust optically thick to the incident radiation, we derive a luminosity of âˆ¼6 Ã— 1044 erg sâˆ’1 for the source heating it. This luminosity is similar to that of the obscured spectral energy distribution, assuming a disk with an Eddington accretion rate of . Alternatively, the dust is illuminated by an unobscured lower luminosity disk with , which permits the UVâ€“optical continuum lags in the high-obscuration state to be dominated by diffuse emission from the broad-line region. Finally, we find hot dust extended on scales â‰³ 140â€“350 pc, associated with the rotating disk of ionised gas we observe in spatially resolved [S III] Î»9531 images. Its likely origin is in the compact bulge of the barred spiral host galaxy, where it is heated by a nuclear starburst.</description><author>The Astrophysical Journal - latest papers</author><pubDate>Mon, 12 Jan 2026 00:00:00 GMT</pubDate><guid isPermaLink="true">https://iopscience.iop.org/article/10.3847/1538-4357/ae17cd</guid></item><item><title>[The Astrophysic] Tidally Driven Inertial Waves Enhance Eccentricity Damping and Spin Evolution in Planets and Stars</title><link>https://iopscience.iop.org/article/10.3847/1538-4357/ae18ca</link><description>Tidal interactions influence the orbital motions of binary star systems and extrasolar planets alike. Tides also affect stellar and planetary rotation rates. We demonstrate that in addition to altering spin synchronization and pseudosynchronization, tidally driven inertial waves in the convective envelopes of low-mass stars and gas-giant planets can enhance tidal eccentricity damping. Analytically, we find that eccentricity damping by inertial waves can be orders of magnitude faster than equilibrium tides, independent of any eddy viscosity prescription. We use simplified numerical experiments to demonstrate this enhancement and to explore the effects of different mixing-length treatments of convective turbulence, as well as a spindown torque from magnetic braking. These calculations demonstrate that tidally driven inertial waves can produce an extended cool core of nearly circular binaries, helping to reconcile a longstanding discrepancy between observed and predicted main-sequence binary circularization. Our calculations additionally suggest that tidally driven inertial waves may leave identifiable signatures in the ratios of the orbital to rotation periods for stellar binaries, including synchronous and subsynchronous rotation periods reminiscent of populations identified in Kepler, TESS, and Gaia data.</description><author>The Astrophysical Journal - latest papers</author><pubDate>Mon, 12 Jan 2026 00:00:00 GMT</pubDate><guid isPermaLink="true">https://iopscience.iop.org/article/10.3847/1538-4357/ae18ca</guid></item><item><title>[The Astrophysic] Preferential Positron Acceleration in Relativistic Magnetized Electronâ€“Positronâ€“Ion Shocks</title><link>https://iopscience.iop.org/article/10.3847/1538-4357/ae246b</link><description>Relativistic shocks are considered efficient accelerators of charged particles and play crucial roles in high-energy astrophysical phenomena, such as gamma-ray bursts and pulsar winds. This study focuses on positron accelerations in magnetized relativistic shocks in electronâ€“positronâ€“ion plasma. Employing 1D ab initio particle-in-cell simulations, we found a preferential positron acceleration through an interaction with the wakefield associated with a precursor wave in the upstream region. Test particle simulations revealed that the selective acceleration occurs for sufficiently large amplitudes of the wakefield. The mechanism can be understood as the relativistic E Ã— B acceleration formulated in the upstream frame. A theoretical analysis of the positron acceleration in astrophysical contexts is presented, supporting ultrarelativistic shocks in pulsar winds as a primary source for the high-energy positron excess.</description><author>The Astrophysical Journal - latest papers</author><pubDate>Mon, 12 Jan 2026 00:00:00 GMT</pubDate><guid isPermaLink="true">https://iopscience.iop.org/article/10.3847/1538-4357/ae246b</guid></item><item><title>[The Astrophysic] Robust Extraction of Global 21 cm Spectrum from Experiments with a Chromatic Beam Based on Physics-motivated Error Modeling</title><link>https://iopscience.iop.org/article/10.3847/1538-4357/ae25ee</link><description>The extraction of the sky-averaged 21 cm signal from Cosmic Dawn and the Epoch of Reionization faces significant challenges. The bright and anisotropic Galactic foreground, which is 4â€“5 orders of magnitude brighter than the 21 cm signal, when convolved with the inevitably chromatic beam, introduces additional spectral structures that can easily mimic the real 21 cm signal. In this paper, we investigate the signal extraction for a lunar-orbit experiment, where the antenna moves fast in orbit and data from multiple orbits have to be used. We propose a physics-motivated and correlated modeling of both the foreground and the measurement errors. By dividing the sky into multiple regions according to the spectral index distribution and accounting for the full covariance of modeling errors, we jointly fit both the foreground and the 21 cm signal using simulated data for the Discovering the Sky at the Longest wavelength lunar orbit experiment. This method successfully extracts the 21 cm signals of various amplitudes from the simulated data even for a testing antenna with a relatively high level of chromaticity. This approach, which is robust against moderate beam chromaticity, significantly relaxes the stringent design and manufacturing requirements for the antenna, offering a practical solution for future 21 cm global signal experiments either on the ground or in space.</description><author>The Astrophysical Journal - latest papers</author><pubDate>Mon, 12 Jan 2026 00:00:00 GMT</pubDate><guid isPermaLink="true">https://iopscience.iop.org/article/10.3847/1538-4357/ae25ee</guid></item><item><title>[The Astrophysic] Ubiquity of Methanol and Its Related Chemical Segregation in Orion Starless Cores: The ALMASOP Sample</title><link>https://iopscience.iop.org/article/10.3847/1538-4357/ae25fd</link><description>Complex organic molecules (COMs) in starless cores provide critical insights into the early stages of star formation and prebiotic chemistry. We present a chemical survey of 16 starless cores (including five prestellar cores) in the Orion A and B molecular clouds, targeting CH3OH, N2H+, CCS, and c-C3HD, using the Atacama Compact Array (ACA) and the Yebes 40 m telescope. CH3OH was detected toward all targets, confirming its ubiquity in starless cores, consistent with previous surveys in Taurus and Perseus. ACA imaging shows that CH3OH, CCS, and c-C3HD generally trace the outer layers of the dense cores outlined by N2H+, each exhibiting distinct spatial distributions. Meanwhile, comparison with Yebes data reveals an extended, flattened CH3OH component. CCS and c-C3HD tend to be detected or nondetected together across cores, while cores near dust-rich regions on a large scale often lack both, suggesting environmental influences linked to the interstellar radiation field. Within individual cores, CCS typically resides in an outer layer relative to c-C3HD. Our findings underscore the importance of high-resolution studies for understanding the origins and spatial differentiation of COMs and carbon-chain molecules in cold, quiescent environments.</description><author>The Astrophysical Journal - latest papers</author><pubDate>Mon, 12 Jan 2026 00:00:00 GMT</pubDate><guid isPermaLink="true">https://iopscience.iop.org/article/10.3847/1538-4357/ae25fd</guid></item><item><title>[The Astrophysic] Ultradiffuse Galaxies in the EAGLE Simulation</title><link>https://iopscience.iop.org/article/10.3847/1538-4357/ae260f</link><description>We use the highest-resolution EAGLE simulation, Recal-L025N0752, to study the properties and formation of ultradiffuse galaxies (UDGs). We identify 181 UDGs at z = 0 and find their properties are consistent with observations. The total masses of the EAGLE UDGs range from âˆ¼5 Ã— 108MâŠ™ to âˆ¼2 Ã— 1011MâŠ™, indicating that they are dwarf galaxies rather than failed Lâ‹† galaxies. The EAGLE UDGs are not a distinct population, but rather a subset of dwarf galaxies, as their properties generally form a continuous distribution with those of normal dwarf galaxies. Unlike most of the situations in previous studies, the extended sizes of the field UDGs in EAGLE are not driven by high halo spins or by supernova-induced stellar expansion, but instead largely arise from high spins in their star-forming gas and thus the newly formed stars at large radii. We hypothesize that this might be attributed to galactic fountains, via which star-forming gas is launched to large halocentric distances and acquires additional angular momentum through interactions with the circumgalactic medium. For satellite UDGs, âˆ¼60% of them were already UDGs before falling into the host galaxy, while the remaining âˆ¼40% were normal galaxies prior to infall and subsequently transformed into UDGs due to tidal effects after infall.</description><author>The Astrophysical Journal - latest papers</author><pubDate>Mon, 12 Jan 2026 00:00:00 GMT</pubDate><guid isPermaLink="true">https://iopscience.iop.org/article/10.3847/1538-4357/ae260f</guid></item><item><title>[The Astrophysic] Consistent Modeling of Nonequilibrium Dust Sublimation and the Interactions with Dust Evolution in the Inner Regions of Protoplanetary Disks</title><link>https://iopscience.iop.org/article/10.3847/1538-4357/ae2683</link><description>The inner regions of protoplanetary disks are host to the sublimation of dust grains, a process traditionally modeled using equilibrium thermodynamics. We demonstrate through ab initio density functional theory and kinetic Monte Carlo simulations that silicate dust sublimation is inherently a nonequilibrium kinetic process. The binding energies and vibrational frequencies governing desorption, calculated for MgSiO3 and other compositions, reveal that sublimation timescales far exceed local dynamical times, allowing grains to persist in a superheated state. This kinetic inhibition results in a broad, dynamic sublimation front whose location and morphology are strongly regulated by radial advection and dust coagulation. Our coupled simulations, integrating sublimation with advection and grain evolution, show that the front varies radially by a factor of four with accretion rate and exhibits a vertically stratified, bowl-shaped structure. These findings imply that the inner diskâ€™s dust distribution, thermal structure, and subsequent planet formation are profoundly influenced by the kinematics and kinetics of dust grains, necessitating a departure from equilibrium prescriptions in disk models and interpretations of inner rim observations.</description><author>The Astrophysical Journal - latest papers</author><pubDate>Mon, 12 Jan 2026 00:00:00 GMT</pubDate><guid isPermaLink="true">https://iopscience.iop.org/article/10.3847/1538-4357/ae2683</guid></item><item><title>[The Astrophysic] Chemical Enrichment of Metal-poor Stars Orbiting Massive Black Hole Companions</title><link>https://iopscience.iop.org/article/10.3847/1538-4357/ae28c6</link><description>There are millions of undetected black holes wandering through our galaxy. Observatories like Chandra, LIGO, and more recently, Gaia, have provided valuable insights into the configurations of these elusive objects when residing in binary systems. Motivated by these advances, we study, for the first time, the enhanced accretion of metals from the interstellar medium (ISM) onto low-mass companions in binary systems with highly unequal mass ratios, utilizing a series of hydrodynamical simulations. Our study demonstrates that a stellar companionâ€™s metal accretion history from the ISM alone, from its formation to the present, can significantly influence its surface abundance, especially when enhanced by a massive black hole companion. However, this effect is likely only measurable in stars that are still on the main sequence. Once a stellar companion evolves off the main sequence, similar to what has been observed with the Gaia BH3 companion, the initial dredge-up process is likely to erase any excess surface abundance resulting from the metals that were accreted. As we discover more unequal mass ratio binary systems, it is crucial to understand how the observed metallicity of Sun-like companions may differ from their birth metallicity, especially if they are not yet evolved.</description><author>The Astrophysical Journal - latest papers</author><pubDate>Mon, 12 Jan 2026 00:00:00 GMT</pubDate><guid isPermaLink="true">https://iopscience.iop.org/article/10.3847/1538-4357/ae28c6</guid></item><item><title>[The Astrophysic] Bayesian Analysis of Wave-optics Gravitationally Lensed Massive Black Hole Binaries with a Space-based Gravitational-wave Detector</title><link>https://iopscience.iop.org/article/10.3847/1538-4357/ae29ad</link><description>Within a Bayesian statistical framework, we jointly estimate the source and lens parameters and evaluate the relative evidence between the lensed and unlensed models. We investigate the wave-optics effects induced by a point-mass lens on gravitational waves (GWs) from massive binary black holes with comparable component masses (q = 0.9) and assess the capability of the space-based GW detector Taiji to detect such effects. Specifically, we investigate the impact of the redshifted lens mass MLz âˆˆ [3 Ã— 105, 3 Ã— 107] MâŠ™, the dimensionless impact parameter y is scaled in terms of the Einstein radius of the lens with y âˆˆ [10, 50], the source redshift zs âˆˆ [4, 6], and the total source mass Ms âˆˆ [105, 107] MâŠ™ on parameter estimation and model selection. Our results indicate that larger MLz values reduce the fitting factor ( ), thereby amplifying the waveform residual and its associated residual signal-to-noise ratio ( ), which enhances the ability to distinguish between lensed and unlensed models. Conversely, for y â‰¥ 50, the approaches 1 and becomes too small to allow effective model discrimination. For y â‰¤ 30, the degeneracy between the luminosity distance dL and MLz can be effectively broken. While the Bayes factor decreases with increasing source redshift zs, lensing signatures remain identifiable up to zs = 6. The influence of the total source mass Ms depends on the overlap of the GW signal with the detectorâ€™s sensitive band. Overall, effective model discrimination generally requires an (corresponding to for the results presented in this work).</description><author>The Astrophysical Journal - latest papers</author><pubDate>Mon, 12 Jan 2026 00:00:00 GMT</pubDate><guid isPermaLink="true">https://iopscience.iop.org/article/10.3847/1538-4357/ae29ad</guid></item><item><title>[The Astrophysic] First Results from the PanRadio Gamma-Ray Burst Collaboration: The 400-day Afterglow of GRB 230815A</title><link>https://iopscience.iop.org/article/10.3847/2041-8213/ae2c8a</link><description>We introduce the PanRadio Gamma-ray Burst (GRB) program carried out on the Australia Telescope Compact Array: a systematic, multiyear, radio survey of all southern Swift GRB events, comprehensively following the multifrequency evolution of their afterglows from within an hour to years postburst. We present the results of the 400-day observing campaign following the afterglow of the long-duration (collapsar) GRB 230815Aâ€”the first one detected through this program. Typically, GRB 230815A would not otherwise receive traditional radio follow-up, given it has no known redshift and lacks comprehensive multiwavelength follow-up, due to its high line-of-sight extinction with AV = 2.3. We found its early X-ray jet break at âˆ¼0.1 days postburst to be at odds with the evolution of the multifrequency radio light curves that were traced over an unusually long duration of 400 days. The radio light curves approximately evolved (with minor deviations) according to the standard self-similar expansion for a relativistic blast wave in a homogeneous environment prior to the jet break, showing no evidence for evolutions of the microphysical parameters describing the electron acceleration processes. We reconcile these features by proposing a two-component jet: the early X-ray break originates from a narrow component with a half-opening angle of âˆ¼2 1, while the evolution of the radio afterglow stems from a wider component with a half-opening angle of âª†35Â°. The PanRadio GRB program will establish a sample of comprehensively followed GRBs, where a rigorous inspection of their microphysical and dynamical parameters can be performed, thereby revealing the diversity of features in their outflows and environments.</description><author>The Astrophysical Journal Letters - latest papers</author><pubDate>Mon, 12 Jan 2026 00:00:00 GMT</pubDate><guid isPermaLink="true">https://iopscience.iop.org/article/10.3847/2041-8213/ae2c8a</guid></item><item><title>[The Astrophysic] No Metallicity Preference in Fast Radio Burst Host Galaxies</title><link>https://iopscience.iop.org/article/10.3847/2041-8213/ae2d19</link><description>Fast radio bursts (FRBs) are millisecond-duration extragalactic radio transients of unknown origin, and studying their host galaxies could offer clues to constrain progenitor models. Among host properties, gas-phase metallicity is a key factor influencing stellar evolution and transient productions. We analyze the largest uniformly selected sample of FRB host galaxies, measuring oxygen abundances ( â€“8.85) for 31 hosts at redshifts z = 0.04â€“0.98, using consistent emission-line diagnostics. Using a volume-limited subsample, we compare the distributions of stellar mass, star formation rate (SFR), and metallicity to a control sample of star-forming galaxies selected by the same criteria. We find that FRB host galaxies span a wide metallicity range and are broadly consistent with the SFR-weighted massâ€“metallicity relation of star-forming galaxies. We find no clear lower metallicity bound, suggesting that FRB progenitors can form in any metallicity environment through channels largely insensitive to metal abundance. Encouragingly, this implies that FRBs can arise even in low-metallicity, high-redshift galaxies, supporting their potential as probes of matter distribution across cosmic time. Additionally, we find marginal (âˆ¼2Ïƒ) evidence for a âˆ’0.09 Â± 0.04 dex metallicity offset from the fundamental metallicity relation. Despite model uncertainties, if real, this offset likely reflects suppressed SFRs at fixed mass and metallicity rather than metal deficiency. Similar offsets are observed in local post-merger galaxies and may reflect a post-starburst phase following galaxy interactions. Such systems may host FRB progenitors formed during the starburst that produce FRBs after a 100â€“500 Myr delay, broadly consistent with observed delay-time distributions, although further data are needed to confirm this interpretation.</description><author>The Astrophysical Journal Letters - latest papers</author><pubDate>Mon, 12 Jan 2026 00:00:00 GMT</pubDate><guid isPermaLink="true">https://iopscience.iop.org/article/10.3847/2041-8213/ae2d19</guid></item><item><title>[The Astrophysic] A Spatial Gap in the Sky Distribution of Fast Radio Burst Detections Coinciding with Galactic Plasma Overdensities</title><link>https://iopscience.iop.org/article/10.3847/2041-8213/ae2eb3</link><description>We analyze the positional and morphological properties of about 3600 unique fast radio burst (FRB) sources reported in the second FRB catalog generated by the Canadian Hydrogen Intensity Mapping Experiment (CHIME) telescope. We find a two-dimensional dependence of FRB detections on sky position and identify a significant absence of detections in a roughly circular region centered at Galactic coordinates (77 7, 0 9), spanning an area of 213.6 deg2. This detection gap spatially coincides with the Cygnus X regionâ€”a plasma-rich star-forming region in the Milky Way. This feature is most likely the result of increased sky temperature and strong multipath scattering by turbulent ionized plasma, which broadens the FRB signals beyond detectability in the CHIME band. Our simulations yield a mean of six expected FRB detections within the gap when accounting for the elevated sky temperature in the direction of the detection gap. We infer that a lower limit of the maximum scattering timescale Ï„sc, 1 GHz â‰¥ 5.59 ms, obtained without assuming a model of the Galactic electron distribution, is sufficient to suppress the brightness of all coincident FRBs. A similar suppression is seen in Catalog 2 along other high emission measure (EM) sight lines (i.e., EM â‰¥ 2900 pc cmâˆ’6), further supporting a broader trend of suppression due to Galactic scattering. Future very long baseline interferometry measurements of scattering disks with CHIME Outriggers can help confirm our interpretation. Our work highlights the notion that FRBs can serve as new, model-independent tracers of the warm ionized medium within our Galaxy.</description><author>The Astrophysical Journal Letters - latest papers</author><pubDate>Mon, 12 Jan 2026 00:00:00 GMT</pubDate><guid isPermaLink="true">https://iopscience.iop.org/article/10.3847/2041-8213/ae2eb3</guid></item><item><title>[The Astrophysic] JWST Spectroscopy of GRB 250702B: An Extremely Rare and Exceptionally Energetic Burst in a Dusty, Massive Galaxy at z = 1.036</title><link>https://iopscience.iop.org/article/10.3847/2041-8213/ae2ed9</link><description>We present follow-up observations of the day-long, repeating gamma-ray burst (GRB) GRB 250702B with the Near Infrared Spectrograph on board the James Webb Space Telescope. Through the identification of narrow hydrogen emission lines at a consistent redshift of z = 1.036 Â± 0.004, we calibrate the distance scale, and therefore the energetics, of this unique extragalactic transient. At this distance, the resulting Î³-ray energy release is at least EÎ³,iso = 2.2 Ã— 1054 erg. We find no evidence for ongoing transient emission at the GRB position and exclude any accompanying supernova (SN) with a luminosity comparable to the Type Ic broad-line SN 2023lcr, though we are unable to rule out a fainter SN counterpart owing to high extinction. The inferred rate of such events, assuming at most one in the lifetime of Fermi, suggests that such bursts are very rare, with volumetric rates over 1000 times lower than normal high-luminosity long GRBs and &gt;105 times lower than core-collapse SNe, when corrected for beaming. Furthermore, we find that the host galaxy is unique among GRB host galaxies and extremely rare in the general galaxy population, being extremely large and dusty and with high stellar mass. The identification of such an exotic GRB in such an unusual galaxy raises the possibility that the environment was important in the progenitor channel creating GRB 250702B.</description><author>The Astrophysical Journal Letters - latest papers</author><pubDate>Mon, 12 Jan 2026 00:00:00 GMT</pubDate><guid isPermaLink="true">https://iopscience.iop.org/article/10.3847/2041-8213/ae2ed9</guid></item><item><title>[The Astronomica] Planetary Habitability Under the Light of a Rapidly Changing Star</title><link>https://iopscience.iop.org/article/10.3847/1538-3881/ae246e</link><description>Planetary atmospheric energy budgets primarily depend on stellar incident flux. However, stellar variability can have major consequences for the evolution of planetary climates. In this work, we evaluate how stellar variability influences the equilibrium temperature and water retention of planets within the habitable zone (HZ). We present a sample of nine stars that are known to host at least one planet within the HZ and that were identified to have a variability amplitude exceeding 100 ppm based on photometry from the Transiting Exoplanet Survey Satellite. We investigate the effect that the variability of these stars has on the insolation flux of their HZ planets and the resulting changes in the induced planetary equilibrium temperature. Our results show that for the stars in our sample, the stellar variability has an insignificant effect on the equilibrium temperature of HZ planets. However, we also emphasize that these stars are not representative of more extreme variable stars, since exoplanets are more difficult to detect and characterize in the presence of extreme variability. We also investigate the equilibrium temperature and long-term evolution of a hypothetical Earth-like planet placed at the inner edge of the HZ around a highly variable star. We found that the water loss rates are comparable between both variable and quiet host stars for Earth-like planets in the inner HZ. Overall, these results broaden our knowledge of the impact of stellar variability on planetary habitability.</description><author>The Astronomical Journal - latest papers</author><pubDate>Mon, 12 Jan 2026 00:00:00 GMT</pubDate><guid isPermaLink="true">https://iopscience.iop.org/article/10.3847/1538-3881/ae246e</guid></item><item><title>[The Astronomica] Keck Observations in the INfrared of Taurus and Ï Oph Exoplanets And Ultracool Dwarfs (KOINTREAU) I: A Planetary-mass Companion and a Disk-obscured Stellar Companion Discovered in Taurus</title><link>https://iopscience.iop.org/article/10.3847/1538-3881/ae267f</link><description>We present the first discoveries from Keck Observations in the Infrared of Taurus and Ï Oph Exoplanets and Ultracool dwarfs (KOINTREAU), an adaptive optics imaging survey of young stars in the Taurus and Ï Oph star-forming regions using the Keck infrared pyramid wavefront sensor. We have found two faint (Î”Kâˆ¼7 mag), wide-separation companions to two â‰ˆ3 Myr old Taurus members. Relative astrometry for these systems shows that both companions are bound to their host stars. We obtained near-infrared spectra of these companions using the Infrared Telescope Facility/SpeX (R âˆ¼100) and the Gemini North InfraRed Spectrograph (Gemini/GNIRS; R âˆ¼ 1000â€“2000), and combined these with photometry from our NIRC2 imaging, the Pan-STARRS survey, and Spitzer/IRAC archival imaging to constrain their properties. One companion, KOINTREAU-1b (at a projected separation of 690 au), has an average near-infrared spectral type of M9 Â± 2, a gravity classification of vl-g, and a changing spectral type between the SpeX (M7) and GNIRS (L1) observations. We estimate this objectâ€™s mass to be MJup, making KOINTREAU-1b the fifth planetary-mass companion found in Taurus. The other companion, KOINTREAU-2b (projected separation 560 au), has a spectral type of M4.5 Â± 1 but is â‰ˆ4 mag underluminous relative to other Taurus stars of the same spectral type. We detect exceptionally strong He I 1.083 Î¼m emission from this object, indicative of outflows driven by ongoing accretion, but with a conspicuous lack of accompanying H emission. We conclude that KOINTREAU-2b is a young star obscured by an edge-on disk and observed in scattered light. Finally, we derive a distortion solution for NIRC2 imaging, which shows a 0 118 difference in position angle from the previous distortion solution.</description><author>The Astronomical Journal - latest papers</author><pubDate>Fri, 09 Jan 2026 00:00:00 GMT</pubDate><guid isPermaLink="true">https://iopscience.iop.org/article/10.3847/1538-3881/ae267f</guid></item><item><title>[Research in Ast] The Influential Roles of Gravity, Turbulence, and Magnetic Fields in Shaping the Physical Evolution of Dense Massive Clumps</title><link>https://iopscience.iop.org/article/10.1088/1674-4527/ae278c</link><description>We explore the roles of the three competitors, namely, gravity, turbulence, and magnetic fields, in controlling star formation within dense, massive clumps identified in the APEX Telescope Large Area Survey of the Galaxy survey. By examining scaling relations, virial parameters, and turbulent energy spectra, we evaluate the dynamical state of these clumps. We observe a weak velocity dispersionâ€“size relation (Ïƒ âˆ L0.11), which is much shallower than the classical Larson-like relations, suggesting that turbulence does not mainly drive internal dynamics. The turbulent energy spectrum, E(k) âˆ kâˆ’1.21, is also less steep than what is expected for both incompressible and compressible turbulence. We equally observe a decreasing trend in the virial parameter with increasing mass (Î±vir âˆ Mâˆ’0.37), indicating that more massive clumps are increasingly gravitationally bound. These trends indicate an increasing relative dominance of gravity over turbulence at smaller scales, aligning with multiscale collapse scenarios; however, the absolute energy balance remains unquantifiable with the current data. Although magnetic fields are not directly measured, their potential influence is considered in the interpretation of pressure balance and dynamical support. Our findings imply that gravitational processes appear to primarily regulate the structure and evolution of massive clumps.</description><author>Research in Astronomy and Astrophysics - latest papers</author><pubDate>Thu, 08 Jan 2026 00:00:00 GMT</pubDate><guid isPermaLink="true">https://iopscience.iop.org/article/10.1088/1674-4527/ae278c</guid></item><item><title>[Recent Articles] Convective stability analysis of massive neutron stars formed in binary mergers</title><link>http://link.aps.org/doi/10.1103/w8gq-3d54</link><description>Author(s): Yong Gao, Kota Hayashi, Kenta Kiuchi, Alan Tsz-Lok Lam, Hao-Jui Kuan, and Masaru Shibata&lt;br /&gt;&lt;p&gt;We perform fully general-relativistic hydrodynamics simulations of binary neutron star mergers over 100Â ms postmerger to investigate the dynamics of remnant massive neutron stars (NSs). Our focus is mainly on the analysis of convective stability and mode characteristics of the massive NSs. We deriveâ€¦&lt;/p&gt;&lt;br /&gt;[Phys. Rev. D 113, 023011] Published Wed Jan 07, 2026</description><author>Recent Articles in Phys. Rev. D</author><pubDate>Wed, 07 Jan 2026 10:00:00 GMT</pubDate><guid isPermaLink="true">http://link.aps.org/doi/10.1103/w8gq-3d54</guid></item><item><title>[Recent Articles] Robust and fast parameter estimation for gravitational waves from binary neutron star merger remnants</title><link>http://link.aps.org/doi/10.1103/g1qs-j74x</link><description>Author(s): Stamatis Vretinaris, Georgios Vretinaris, Christos Mermigkas, Minas Karamanis, and Nikolaos Stergioulas&lt;br /&gt;&lt;p&gt;We present a robust and efficient methodology for parameter estimation of gravitational waves generated during the postmerger phase of binary neutron star mergers. Our approach leverages an analytic waveform model combined with empirical relations to predict prior ranges for the postmerger frequenciâ€¦&lt;/p&gt;&lt;br /&gt;[Phys. Rev. D 113, 024012] Published Wed Jan 07, 2026</description><author>Recent Articles in Phys. Rev. D</author><pubDate>Wed, 07 Jan 2026 10:00:00 GMT</pubDate><guid isPermaLink="true">http://link.aps.org/doi/10.1103/g1qs-j74x</guid></item><item><title>[Recent Articles] Entanglement is protected by acceleration-induced transparency in thermal field</title><link>http://link.aps.org/doi/10.1103/z6nb-gjry</link><description>Author(s): Yongjie Pan, Baocheng Zhang, and Qingyu Cai&lt;br /&gt;&lt;p&gt;The acceleration-induced transparency (AIT) effect has been suggested recently to amplify the transition probability of the two-level detector and offers a potential avenue for the experimental detection of the Unruh effect. In this paper, we explore the influence of the AIT effect on quantum entangâ€¦&lt;/p&gt;&lt;br /&gt;[Phys. Rev. D 113, 025004] Published Wed Jan 07, 2026</description><author>Recent Articles in Phys. Rev. D</author><pubDate>Wed, 07 Jan 2026 10:00:00 GMT</pubDate><guid isPermaLink="true">http://link.aps.org/doi/10.1103/z6nb-gjry</guid></item><item><title>[Nature] Insights into DNA repeat expansions among 900,000 biobank participants</title><link>https://www.nature.com/articles/s41586-025-09886-z</link><description>&lt;p&gt;Nature, Published online: 07 January 2026; &lt;a href="https://www.nature.com/articles/s41586-025-09886-z"&gt;doi:10.1038/s41586-025-09886-z&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;Human genetic variation influences instability of DNA repeats that commonly expand as we age.</description><author>Nature</author><pubDate>Wed, 07 Jan 2026 00:00:00 GMT</pubDate><guid isPermaLink="true">https://www.nature.com/articles/s41586-025-09886-z</guid></item><item><title>[Nature] The complex role of nutrients in cancer spread</title><link>https://www.nature.com/articles/d41586-025-03988-4</link><description>&lt;p&gt;Nature, Published online: 07 January 2026; &lt;a href="https://www.nature.com/articles/d41586-025-03988-4"&gt;doi:10.1038/d41586-025-03988-4&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;An in-depth analysis of nutrient availability across mouse tissues reveals their influence on the spread of cancer to other organs.</description><author>Nature</author><pubDate>Wed, 07 Jan 2026 00:00:00 GMT</pubDate><guid isPermaLink="true">https://www.nature.com/articles/d41586-025-03988-4</guid></item><item><title>[Recent Articles] Influence of supermassive primordial black holes on ultraviolet luminosity of high-redshift galaxies</title><link>http://link.aps.org/doi/10.1103/sqq1-vwq6</link><description>Author(s): Yi-Yang Li, Hai-Long Huang, and Yun-Song Piao&lt;br /&gt;&lt;p&gt;Recently James Webb Space Telescope (JWST) have observed an excess of luminous galaxies at high redshifts ($zâ‰³10$). In this work, we investigate whether supermassive primordial black holes (SMPBHs) can explain it by their influence on the ultraviolet luminosity function (UV LF) of high-redshift galaâ€¦&lt;/p&gt;&lt;br /&gt;[Phys. Rev. D 113, 023008] Published Tue Jan 06, 2026</description><author>Recent Articles in Phys. Rev. D</author><pubDate>Tue, 06 Jan 2026 10:00:00 GMT</pubDate><guid isPermaLink="true">http://link.aps.org/doi/10.1103/sqq1-vwq6</guid></item><item><title>[Recent Articles] Formation of Voids or Stacking-Fault Tetrahedra Induced by Local Chemical Variations in Face-Centered-Cubic Complex Concentrated Alloys</title><link>http://link.aps.org/doi/10.1103/p629-97jn</link><description>Author(s): Yeping Lin, Chenyang Lu, Tengfei Yang, Zhengxiong Su, Yixin Deng, Wangyu Hu, Huiqiu Deng, Guanghong Lu, and Fei Gao&lt;br /&gt;&lt;p&gt;Understanding how elemental variations influence defect cluster formation is a longstanding challenge in materials science. By combining defect rates-based long-time dynamics with molecular dynamics and irradiation experiments, we identify a distinct, cluster-mediated mechanismâ€”governed by element-sâ€¦&lt;/p&gt;&lt;br /&gt;[Phys. Rev. Lett. 136, 016102] Published Tue Jan 06, 2026</description><author>Recent Articles in Phys. Rev. Lett.</author><pubDate>Tue, 06 Jan 2026 10:00:00 GMT</pubDate><guid isPermaLink="true">http://link.aps.org/doi/10.1103/p629-97jn</guid></item><item><title>[The Astrophysic] J-HERTz: J-PLUS Heritage Exploration of Radio Targets at z &lt; 5</title><link>https://iopscience.iop.org/article/10.3847/1538-4365/ae2016</link><description>We introduce J-HERTz (J-PLUS Heritage Exploration of Radio Targets at z &lt; 5), a new multiwavelength catalog that combines optical narrowband photometry from J-PLUS, infrared observations from the Wide-field Infrared Survey Explorer, and deep low-frequency radio data from LoTSS for nearly 0.5 million sources across 2100 deg2 of the northern sky. Key innovations of J-HERTz include Bayesian neural network classifications for 390,000 galaxies, 31,000 quasars, and 20,000 stars, along with significantly improved photometric redshifts for 235,000 galaxies compared to previous J-PLUS DR3 and LoTSS DR2 estimates. We identify 831 candidate Galactic radio stars, which, if confirmed, would constitute a significant addition to the number of radio-emitting stars identified to date. Among radio-loud galaxies with spectroscopic observations, â‰³20% lack Seyfert or LINER signatures, indicating a substantial population of optically quiescent radio galaxies, in agreement with previous works. Spectral energy distribution fitting of their host galaxies using J-PLUS photospectra reveals systematically low specific star formation rates, consistent with quenched stellar populations. J-HERTz thus provides a powerful data set to exploit radio-optical synergies, enabling studies that span from the origin of stellar radio emission to the active galactic nucleus life cycle and the role of jet activity in shaping host galaxy evolution.</description><author>The Astrophysical Journal Supplement Series - latest papers</author><pubDate>Tue, 06 Jan 2026 00:00:00 GMT</pubDate><guid isPermaLink="true">https://iopscience.iop.org/article/10.3847/1538-4365/ae2016</guid></item><item><title>[The Astrophysic] The Green Bank Ammonia Survey: Data Release 2</title><link>https://iopscience.iop.org/article/10.3847/1538-4365/ae11b1</link><description>We present an overview of the final data release (DR2) from the Green Bank Ammonia Survey (GAS). GAS is a large program at the Green Bank Telescope to map all Gould Belt star-forming regions with AV â‰³ 7 mag visible from the Northern Hemisphere in emission from NH3 and other key molecular tracers. This final release includes the data for all the regions observed: Heiles Cloud 2 and B18 in Taurus; Barnard 1, Barnard 1-E, IC 348, NGC 1333, L1448, L1451, and Per7/34 in Perseus; L1688 and L1689 in Ophiuchus; Orion A (North and South) and Orion B in Orion; Cepheus; B59 in Pipe; Corona Australis East and West; IC 5146; and Serpens Aquila and MWC297 in Serpens. Similar to what was presented in GAS DR1, we find that the NH3 emission and dust continuum emission from Herschel correspond closely. We find that the NH3 emission is generally extended beyond the typical 0.1 pc length scales of dense cores, and we find that the transition between coherent core and turbulent cloud is a common result. This shows that the regions of coherence are common throughout different star-forming regions, with a substantial fraction of the high column density regions displaying subsonic nonthermal velocity dispersions. We produce maps of the gas kinematics, temperature, and NH3 column densities through forward modeling of the hyperfine structure of the NH3 (1,1) and (2,2) lines. We show that the NH3 velocity dispersion, Ïƒv, and gas kinetic temperature, TK, vary systematically between the regions included in this release, with an increase in both the mean value and spread of Ïƒv and TK with increasing star formation activity. The data presented in this paper are publicly available via doi:10.11570/24.0091.</description><author>The Astrophysical Journal Supplement Series - latest papers</author><pubDate>Fri, 02 Jan 2026 00:00:00 GMT</pubDate><guid isPermaLink="true">https://iopscience.iop.org/article/10.3847/1538-4365/ae11b1</guid></item><item><title>[Recent Articles] Self-Propulsion via Nontransitive Phase Coexistence in Chemically Active Mixtures</title><link>http://link.aps.org/doi/10.1103/7n1c-2m5g</link><description>Author(s): Yicheng Qiang, Chengjie Luo, and David Zwicker&lt;br /&gt;&lt;p&gt;Chemical activity is central in active matter, where local fuel consumption can lead to self-propulsion and phase separation. However, phase separation can also originate from passive physical interactions. To understand the influence of chemical activity on phase separation, we study mixtures whereâ€¦&lt;/p&gt;&lt;br /&gt;[Phys. Rev. Lett. 135, 268301] Published Wed Dec 24, 2025</description><author>Recent Articles in Phys. Rev. Lett.</author><pubDate>Wed, 24 Dec 2025 10:00:00 GMT</pubDate><guid isPermaLink="true">http://link.aps.org/doi/10.1103/7n1c-2m5g</guid></item><item><title>[Publications of] The Dependence of Earth Milankovitch Cycles on Martian Mass</title><link>https://iopscience.iop.org/article/10.1088/1538-3873/ae2800</link><description>The Milankovitch cycles of Earth result from gravitational interactions with other bodies in the solar system. These interactions lead to slow changes in the orbit and angular momentum vector of Earth, and correspondingly influence Earthâ€™s climate evolution. Several studies have shown that Mars may play a significant role in these Milankovitch cycles, such as the 2.4 Myr eccentricity cycle related to perihelion precession dynamics. Here we provide the results of a detailed dynamical analysis that explores the Earth Milankovitch cycles as a function of the Martian mass to quantify the extent that Mars influences variations in Earthâ€™s orbital eccentricity, the longitude of perihelion, the longitude of the ascending node, and obliquity (axial tilt). Our results show that, although the 405 kyr long-eccentricity metronome driven by g2 (Venus) and g5 (Jupiter) persists at all Mars masses, the âˆ¼100 kyr short-eccentricity bands driven by g4 (Mars) lengthen and gain power as Mars becomes more massive, consistent with enhanced coupling among inner-planet g-modes. The 2.4 Myr grand cycle is absent when Mars approaches zero mass, reflecting the movement of g4 with the Martian mass. Meanwhile, Earthâ€™s obliquity cycles driven by s3 (Earth) and s4 (Mars) lengthen from the canonical âˆ¼41 kyr with increasing Mars mass, relocating to a dominant 45â€“55 kyr band when the mass of Mars is an order of magnitude larger than its present value. These results establish how Marsâ€™ mass controls the architecture of Earthâ€™s climate-forcing spectrum and that the Milankovitch spectrum of an Earth-like planet is a sensitive, interpretable probe of its planetary neighborhood.</description><author>Publications of the Astronomical Society of the Pacific - latest papers</author><pubDate>Thu, 18 Dec 2025 00:00:00 GMT</pubDate><guid isPermaLink="true">https://iopscience.iop.org/article/10.1088/1538-3873/ae2800</guid></item></channel></rss>